<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Knaves and fooles in folio. Discovered, and then advised, that once at the last they will grow both wise and honest. Or, a meanes to undeceive, and so to beget a right understanding and judgement throughout the three kingdomes, hitherto deluded by the aforesaids. Dedicated with all respectivenesse both for discovery and caution against the aforesaids, to all the wise and honest of the three nations, whom wee highly prize and honour, especially the Honourable Citie of London, whose goodnesse, piety, easie betrust, and credulity of such unworthies, hath been too much wrought upon and abused by depraved polititians of all sorts. In which tract is shewed the wickednesse of the one side in their severall pretences, and the weaknesse on the other side, in being through too much credulity surprized and circumvented by such pretenders, who intend not what they pretend; but bave [sic] their own self-ends to compasse under such pretexts. -Conceived very usefull to be taken knowledge of, by all sorts whatsoever. For that wee hope the reader will finde himselfe fully satisfied thereby, which may probably much check, if not totally break the neck of this uncivill Civill Warre. The contents of the booke are in the next page.</title>
            <author>S. H.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E462_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86119)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E462[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Knaves and fooles in folio. Discovered, and then advised, that once at the last they will grow both wise and honest. Or, a meanes to undeceive, and so to beget a right understanding and judgement throughout the three kingdomes, hitherto deluded by the aforesaids. Dedicated with all respectivenesse both for discovery and caution against the aforesaids, to all the wise and honest of the three nations, whom wee highly prize and honour, especially the Honourable Citie of London, whose goodnesse, piety, easie betrust, and credulity of such unworthies, hath been too much wrought upon and abused by depraved polititians of all sorts. In which tract is shewed the wickednesse of the one side in their severall pretences, and the weaknesse on the other side, in being through too much credulity surprized and circumvented by such pretenders, who intend not what they pretend; but bave [sic] their own self-ends to compasse under such pretexts. -Conceived very usefull to be taken knowledge of, by all sorts whatsoever. For that wee hope the reader will finde himselfe fully satisfied thereby, which may probably much check, if not totally break the neck of this uncivill Civill Warre. The contents of the booke are in the next page.</title>
                  <author>S. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 36 [i.e. 37], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons for R[alph] H[arford] in Queens-head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: S.H.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from the Huntington Library catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The kingdome how deluded by knaves and fooles in folio.</note>
                  <note>P. 37 misnumbered 36.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. ye 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114919:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Knaves and Fooles IN FOLIO.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered, and then Adviſed, that once at the laſt they will grow both wiſe and honeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or,</hi> A Meanes to undeceive, and ſo to beget a right underſtanding and judgement throughout the three Kingdomes, hitherto deluded by the aforeſaids.</p>
            <p>Dedicated with all reſpectiveneſſe both for diſcovery and caution againſt the aforeſaids, to all the wiſe and honeſt of the three Nations, whom wee highly prize and honour, eſpecially the Honourable Citie of <hi>London,</hi> whoſe goodneſſe, piety, eaſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt, and credulity of ſuch unworthies, hath been too much wrought upon and abuſed by depraved Polititians of all ſorts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In which Tract is ſhewed the wickedneſſe of the one ſide in their ſeverall pretences, and the weakneſſe on the other ſide, in being through too much credulity ſurprized and circumvented by ſuch pretenders, who intend not what they pretend; but bave their own ſelf-ends to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe under ſuch pretexts.—Conceived very uſefull to be taken know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of, by all ſorts whatſoever. For that wee hope the Reader will finde himſelfe fully ſatisfied thereby, which may probably much check, if not totally break the neck of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncivill Civill Warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>The deafe Adder will not heare, charme thou never ſo wiſely, nor will fooles bray'd in morters, forſake their follies.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>But rebuke a wiſe man and he will love thee,—whereas a foole rebuked will hate thee.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The Contents of the Booke are in the next Page.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons</hi> for <hi>R. H.</hi> In Queens-head-Alley. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:114919:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Booke in general are about divers errours and miſtakes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple concerning the Kingdome, the Parliament, the King, and laſtly themſelves in particular, fully cleared, and all, or moſt of their Objections anſwered.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſeverall particular Contents are as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. THat the State at large is King, and the King ſo called is but its Steward or higheſt Officer; alſo not ſelfely higheſt, but made ſo by the favour of the people, in oppoſition to particulars, not the generall, ſee <hi>Sect.</hi> 46. 58, 59.</item>
               <item>2. That the welfare of the ſame State in Peace, Juſtice, and ſafety, &amp;c. is the end of the ſaid Steward and Officer, and ſo is it the Higheſt power and ſo King and Soveraign of all Deputy-powers whatſoever, &amp;c. <hi>ſee</hi> 46 58 59.</item>
               <item>3. The peoples errour in their vaſt acceptation of the title, King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</hi> cleered at <hi>Sect.</hi> 63. the margent alſo. So concerning his Dues or Rights any way, as the Crown, Throne, Scepter, &amp;c. <hi>ſee</hi> 53 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'th margent, ſo all of 58.</item>
               <item>4. The peoples unjuſt Objections and Exceptions againſt the Parliament anſwered, and their juſt ones complyed too, and provided for, at 29. 30. 47, 48. to 56, 57. As for Royalliſts and Malignants in ſpeciall. <hi>See</hi> 55.</item>
               <item>5. That the Parliament (as they ſay) hath wronged them more then the King: and that they are as very ſlaves as the King can or will make them, &amp;c. ſee the next afore: ſo alſo in full, <hi>ſect.</hi> 71.</item>
               <item>6. Till the King come home (as they ſay) no Peace nor ſettlement will be. Anſwered at—72.</item>
               <item>7. Their miſtakes and errours about the Treaty; alſo the wicked policy of ſome to deceive the ſimple about the ſame, diſcovered: ſee <hi>Sect.</hi> 21. and Iſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</item>
               <item>8. That they, (as they ſay) fight for the Kingdome and themſelves, and not againſt, &amp;c. In fighting for the King againſt the Parliament; alſo that they ought to fight for the Kings Rights, Dues, &amp; cs. the Covenant likewiſe binding tbem thereto.—73.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114919:3"/>
9. They fight againſt the Parliament as wrongers of the King and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp;c. 74.</item>
               <item>10. Concerning Religion, ſo <hi>Independents</hi> and Sects, the peoples mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes and exceptions about them, cleered, <hi>ſect.</hi> 54. ſee the margent alſo.</item>
               <item>11. Divers Quaeries concerning Treaſon, Rebellion, and diſobedience, in relation to the State at large, the Parliament, the King, and the Army; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo concerning ſideing with, or againſt any of them, or newtralizing, uſefully reſolved, ſatisfyed, and cleered, from <hi>ſect.</hi> 59. to 63.</item>
               <item>12. An addition of ſome Quaeries or Particulars more concerning the next aforeſaid Subject, ſet downe, becauſe omitted there, as at <hi>ſect.</hi> 65, 66, 67.</item>
               <item>13. The title King not rightly tranſlated from any Language: ſee <hi>ſect.</hi> 63. all the margent.</item>
               <item>14. Alſo who are Murtherers and Theeves in this Warre; who not, ſee <hi>ſect.</hi> 68, 69.</item>
               <item>15. An application to the Parliament, at <hi>ſect.</hi> 64.</item>
               <item>16. Another to <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>ſect.</hi> 63.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114919:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F our Adverſaries write all, or any thing, and we nothing at all, the conquering Sword will bee conquered by the Pen; ſo alſo, Juſtice, Piety, and Purity by pravities—It may not bee, which rather then it ſhall, we the meaneſt of many, have in love to juſtice, and integrity, for the common good of this our diſtracted and almoſt deſtroyed Nation, adventured the combat: For we expect rather wicked (though weake Sophiſticall, and brangling) oppoſitions, then a genuine Reply, or Compliance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So reſt I thine, S. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:114919:4"/>
GOod Reader, our earneſt deſire to give full ſatisfaction, hath inlarged the Margine, which I pray thee faile not to read, leſt thou come ſhort of our intention,—thine inſtruction—</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114919:4"/>
            <head>Knaves &amp; Fooles <hi>In Folio</hi> Diſcovered and adviſed.</head>
            <head>SECTION I.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Alwayes took Men for Men, till now of late; and now I finde them Fiends, and Monſters, and withall monſtrous Fooles: Monſters they are, as murthering men like themſelves, and in murthering themſelves alſo, by in inforcing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers defenſively to kill them; which in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcer, is murther, in the inforced killing: I ſay, unjuſt offenders or defenders, are murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: But the juſt offender, or defender, may kill, but cannot murther.</p>
            <p>2. But to the poynt, There is a crew of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lunsford, Langdale, Goring</hi> the Monopoliſt, <hi>Culpepper, Hopton, Glenham.</hi> &amp;c. Under the Kings, the Princes, or Dukes names, (which the ſilly people idolatrize) they proclaim, ſummon, or demand Forts, Towers, Towns, Caſtles, &amp;c. And bribe for them, write letters, give commiſſions, and all is for themſelves, &amp;c. Will the Lords of their own yeeld them up to the treacherous Steward, their right and might, &amp;c?</note> crafty knaves and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors lately returned into the Kingdome, who formerly pretended the King, but intended themſelves onely; ſo politickly to deceive the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they made uſe of the Kings name to draw the people on their ſide, who thought they fought for the King, but it was to raiſe the fortunes of theſe fellowes, by raiſing themſelves. And thus thoſe crafty knaves cauſed the poore ignorant ſottiſh people to murther one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make themſelves great; for which the Fooles were jeered by theſe Knaves, &amp;c. And withall theſe Knaves applauded and magnified themſelves for this their act of gullery and knavery.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:114919:5"/>
3. The ſame perſons are now come again to act the ſecond, yet <note place="margin">The <hi>Scot</hi> will alſo gull fools under the ſame pretenſes, and then Beavers muſt vaile Bonnets to Blew-caps.</note> the ſame part or Tragedy, to the ſame Tune, under the ſame pretences for the King, Liberties, Lawes, &amp;c. But it's for the ſame end of ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inveſtment and advancement, as afore unto their own, and above their own if they can.</p>
            <p>4. For they <hi>(Demetrius-like)</hi> care not a Ruſh for <hi>Diana:</hi> ſo, nor they for the King, but to King themſelves. Or, as the one lived by making ſilver Shrines, and theſe by Shrines of Silver.</p>
            <p>5. For what's the King, or <hi>Diana</hi> to either of them, but as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing?</p>
            <p>6. What mad fooles are all ſorts to be ſo gul'd, and led by the noſe, and jeet'd at for their folly? to think theſe Rake-ſhames, who fought againſt the Kingdome, as before, under pretence for the King, (a fine piece of <note n="*" place="margin">As againſt the Kingdom, the Kings King, &amp;c.</note> treaſon) yet all to bring about their owne ends, as to advance themſelves over the Kingdome, and King it both over it and the King; yet ſhew the King to the people. Who but fooles, I ſay, can think theſe fight for the King, &amp;c. and not for themſelves? And how agrees it with the duty of faithfulneſſe to the Kingdome (their Mother) to fight for the King her ſervant (did they truly ſo) againſt it <note place="margin">See to it yee fooles what you doe, they have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the King, nor can the King give Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,—would he give it.</note> or her, and ſo againſt theire own alſo, in concluſion.</p>
            <p>7. Is it poſſible? Can Libertines ſettle the Liberties of others? or the irreligious Religion? Can the godleſſe be for God? Can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries concentrize? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>8. Their return now, is but to ſerve their own turn, though their pretences be as afore<hi>:</hi> It's onely, I ſay, to cauſe the people (under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour as for the King, Religion, and Liberties) to aid them (to the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of one another) to help them to their lands, livings and <note place="margin">Do fooles, do, ſpoyle your grain, and ſo your gaine, by rampant horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Sowed you to reap ſo? Doe, ſend them money and means to inable them to take away your meanes, &amp;c.</note> meanes, as alſo their preferments, offices, Monopolies again, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>9. Fooles that you are, beſides the aforeſaids, it's alſo to conquer you by your ſelves, by your follies, &amp;c. As by your ignorance, credulity, and eaſie betruſt, and then to rule over you as Conquerours, and put all on the King, as if onely his doings; for which they are hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſorry, but cannot help it, though they be the onely helpers and hurters, as having power, but not wit, but wilfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>10. You have fought againſt them formerly for the kingdome, and your ſelves; as, for your Religion and Liberties, &amp;c. Why fight you for ſuch as fought againſt you, and you againſt them in the foreſaids? and they have ſtill the ſame intention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you fooles, ſee you not your folly? Will not braying in a mortar make you leave it, and grow wiſe? I ſee you have no other eyes but eyes, &amp;c,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114919:5"/>
11. The King fought againſt you in the ſame particulars, and you againſt him by way of defence, for your ſelves. He fights ſtill, yet more covertly and cunningly, againſt you, for the ſame ends; and by you, to end you, and begin himſelfe a-new.</p>
            <p>12. Why fight you not againſt him, as afore? Or why fought you againſt him before? Or why, of all whyes, fight you now for him, or on his ſide, againſt your ſelves, and your poſterities? Sure you are beſides your ſelves, that you thus ſide not with your ſelves, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>13. Fooles of all ſorts, what think you? Will not the King and <note place="margin">Are not thoſe Clergymen, ſo all ſorts tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their countrey ſo? Are they not murtherers that give way to the peoples murthering for their own ends; how then to plot all? &amp;c.</note> theſe Traytors, theſe Prevaricators, &amp;c. be revenged on all ſorts, Presbyters as Independents, Layicks as Clergy-men, for outing him the Viceroy, and theſe his vicious Royaliſts, and his pragmaticall Prelats? Do Presbyter, do, flatter thy ſelfe, as <hi>Agag,</hi> the feare of death is paſt<hi>:</hi> But know (young man) for all this, thou ſhalt come to judgement; and as thy ſword hath made many a woman childleſſe, ſo ſhall thy mother be chidleſſe this day—Precipitation waits on proſtraters, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>14. And you Citizens, as civilly and demurely as you look, it will not do, you have had a finger in the pye, &amp;c. It's you monied the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt the King: ſo againſt the Prelats, and that Faction; it will fraction you, if ever they come to be whole againe: they may <note n="*" place="margin">Come in, my Lord, come in: but for I this <hi>Jael</hi> drives tbe naile into his Temples.</note> ſmile on you, and you may <hi>(Agag-</hi>like) flatter and befoole your ſelves with <hi>the feare of death is paſt;</hi> but be ſure they will ſmite you under the fifth rib.</p>
            <p>15. And what can you expect from ſuch Leaders and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as aforeſaid, but to be led like ſlaves, or beaſts, and commanded like fooles? What are the Citizens as very fooles as the foole? For ſhame, learn wit and wiſdome, or ſuffer like wiſeakers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>16. For my part, I did never ſee ſuch adventurous fooles in all my life, that will hazard Life, Liberties, and Religion, &amp;c. on bare words; of the woordy, of irreligious Rakeſhames, that helpt to perjure it in the North, and call God to witneſſe it, that they intended no ſuch thing as raiſing of Armes, though raiſing of Arms was their onely intention.</p>
            <p>17. Words and Mottoes for God, Religion, &amp;c. are but words, and words are made of lettetrs, and yet letters are lets to the <note n="*" place="margin">Opinion pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions up judgement.</note> underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of many, when they look at them, and not to things, to real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114919:6"/>
18. You fooles of all ſorts, Is it nothing to engage Life, Liberty and Religion on bare words of ſuch <hi>Recreants?</hi> What, for nothing? Are the aforeſaids things of no value? In other matters you will not truſt the Truſty without ſecurity, no not with trivials, and will you truſt the truſtleſſe with life, Religion, livelihood, and liberties? You fooles, why engage you, or think to engage, before they ingage ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſecurity, that theſe things (they having victorized) you ſhall have without any intruſions to your hurt or confuſion, &amp;c. You Calves, will you go like Oxen to the ſlaughter, or like Fooles to the ſtockes with laughter? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>19. Well, the King they will have home, I that they will, and ſo <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> If he come in a conquerour, there is no law but luſt, no lives, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, religion, or eſtates, but <hi>ad placitum.</hi> Then the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia his, he wil maſter all at his pleaſure; with the Navie he will bring in Forraigners to force all, and he will gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon all Countries with his Faction, and inforce the Countries to pay for the rods that muſt whip them. And he and his Queen will jeere, ſcorn, and inſult over the fooliſh Engliſh, and make them work to maintain their revelling, &amp;c. He will alſo diſarm all, &amp; onely Arm his party: Then will he do with you, ſo yours, to take your Sonnes and Daughters, your Fields and Vineyards as he pleaſeth.</note> will you: more knaves and fooles are you both. Nay, are you not mad men as well as fooles? Will you have him home without cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſecurity from him and them, againſt his and their beſlaving you? If you bring him home like a Conquerour, it's you the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours are conquered, and leave your poſterities ſlaves, and capable of curſing you their fooliſh fathers, &amp;c. I have told you before, and now tell you again, They pretend the King onely to draw you on, but onely intend themſelves, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>20. Was <hi>Kent</hi> never conquered hitherto? And ſhall their follies now foile and conquer them? Fooles, be wiſe for ſhame, know and be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <note place="margin">See Sect. 44. if fit to treat with. So Sect. 46. Is not the Kingdome Lord &amp; King, &amp;c. Se Sect. 46. Is it for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the guiltleſs Lord to treat with his guilty ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant? I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſht at its baſeneſſe, &amp;c.</note> that you be ſecured (and that not with words, for they are wind) of ſafe and juſt conditions before you entertain him, that ſo you and your poſterities may live free, according to your birth-rights, and not as ſlaves. Remember the Northern proteſtations and oathes broken, being ſo ſolemnly taken at his coronation; doe they not crowne all for fooles that truſt any further then groundedly ſecured?</p>
            <p>21. <hi>To treate with,</hi> is the pretence, but the intention is to make uſe of the ignorant and giddy-brain'd idolatrizing people, to throng in threans and multitudes to him, and ſo over-power themſelves and theirs; yea, the whole kingdome with their weight and levity. He will then ſcorn to <hi>treat</hi> or <hi>intreat,</hi> but will intreat all his oppoſers as his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers. How think you fools? will that be? Surely to your not being; when it will bee too late to help either your ſelves or your poſterities, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114919:6"/>
22 Oh but the Citizens, no, nor the Countries, will not fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Kent, Eſſex,</hi> nor any the Countries, they will rather fight for them, &amp;c. But know they what's for them?<hi>—See Sect.</hi> 24, 27, 33.</p>
            <p>23. What, are the grave Citizens ſuch fooles, what if <hi>againſt Kent</hi> or <hi>Eſſex</hi> be <hi>for them,</hi> however for the kngdome: how then, I ſay?</p>
            <p>24. Is all <hi>Kent</hi> or <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or the Countries thus befool'd? I cannot think it; but admit ſo, we ought be againſt them in all unjuſtneſſe or endangerings to themſelves or the kingdome; and in being <hi>againſt,</hi> we are <hi>for.</hi> Fooles know, it's not words, or expreſſions, or oculars define, but things, natures, intentions, intrinſiques, and occults.</p>
            <p>25. We ought alſo to be for our ſelves, and ours in ſafety and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſo for the kingdome, and that firſt of all, though againſt the Countries, if ſo it were; but ſo it is not, but for them. Alſo—&amp;c.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Kent</hi> and the Countries promiſe well in ſuch and ſuch particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars as appeares by their petition and its Comment. The Comment ſpeakes commendably, and better then the Petition, what then? Theſe are but words, who ſhall ſecure us, that, that is their intentions one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? May it not be to inſinuate, and ſo by degrees (in the interim) to gather company to ſide with them, and ſtave off all oppoſers: for who would not ſide with, and who will oppoſe ſuch petitioners, ſuch Commenters, if their aimes reacht not beyond their words and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes?</p>
            <p>26. And therefore yet again, who but fooles would ſide with them, &amp;c. ſuch and ſuch being their Leaders, Heads and Commanders? and who but Fooles, Knaves, or both, would not oppoſe them, having ſuch petitionary commands, and proſtrating Commanders,—ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they change their Commanders, ſo their commands and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>of forcibly bringing in the King;</hi> they are not to be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with, but commined rather, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>27. If you will not be againſt the Countries, but for them, then open their underſtandings by diſcovering the adverſaries cunning pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and deceits, and the error of ſome particulars in their petitions, <note place="margin">Let the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſmite me, and it ſhall bee a kindneſſe: let him reprove, and it ſhall be an excellent oyle.</note> &amp;c. Oppoſe them in this ſenſe, for their own and the kingdomes good. <hi>Better are the rebukes of a friend, then the kiſſes of an enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>28. Blandiſhments blind fooles, but friendly checkes open the eyes of the wiſe.—But who is ſo faithfull to give them, or ſo wiſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of them?</p>
            <p>29. Well, but the Parliament hath abuſed you and them, &amp;c. as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114919:7"/>
you object and except; but admit ſo, ſo now you will not comply to them any longer, but defie, &amp;c. What then? Will you right you ſelfe the wrong way? Will you out of the Frying pan into the fire? Is not pinching better then fleying? &amp;c. But know fooles, the Parliament is forced for neceſſity and policy ſake, to doe many things they would nor, and deny many things they would grant, and to conceale many diſcoverables, becauſe time is not yet for them: and you are brainleſſe, ignorant, opinionated, and wilfull withall; and ſo not able to beare or digeſt them, though for your good, ſuch is your badneſſe.</p>
            <p>30 Hath the Parliament wrong'd you? Admit ſo, what then? will you accept therefore no righting at all, nor any right things from them? Sure in not complying to you in your prepoſterous pretended treaty with the King, intended fiding with him to inſlave your ſelves and your poſterities, and the whole kingdome; they have righted you, and complyed to you, in that they have not complied to you for your deſtructions, by murthers, loſſe of friends, husbands, parents, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, alſo in that they would preſerve your grain, your fruit on the ground, which the rampant horſes would have ground to powder for you, and againſt you, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>31. In ſhort, be wiſe at laſt, ſuſpect and ſearch into the pretenſes of your ſuggeſters and prompters of ſuch petitions, they have their own ends, not yours, except your ending. Remember what your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders are, and their ends, &amp;c. many their Officers are for plunder, and whats yours, more then for you, &amp;c. Clergy-men are many of them great cheaters of the people for their own ends, urging <hi>(Demetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> like) <hi>Diana, Diana;</hi> ſo they the King, God, Religion, Liberties, and againſt the Parliament, but all is for you to fight to force them under the ground aforeſaid, till you are groundleſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>32. Inforce not the Parliament by importunities, (as <hi>Phaeton</hi> did <hi>Phoebus)</hi> for the guidance of the Sunnes Chariot; it's beyond your management, keep in your orbs and ſpheares of underſtanding and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, leſt you be out-reacht, yea leſt you out-reach your ſelves, which is ſoon done by reachleſneſſe and ignorance, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>33. But yet again, the Citie will not fight againſt the Countrey, leſt the Countries combine againſt them. A fine pretence and a fooliſh feare, becauſe the greater feare ſhould feare away the leſſe. As for aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or being againſt, what is ſo, ſee before at Sect. 27. Inform them well, and you ſhall form them anew, and they ſhall finde it's for them. Am I againſt my father, or am I not rather for him, if in his error,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114919:7"/>
wilfulneſſe, or paſſion, he were ready to perpetrate murder, or treaſon, &amp;c. if I diſarm and withſtand him, judge your ſelves, doe not I ſave him? So the deſigned object alſo from deſtruction, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>34. Theres no ſuch for's, as ſuch againſts, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>35. And why rather feare you not this greater feare, that for want of aiding the Army againſt (as you ſay) but I ſay for the Countries againſt the <hi>Goreans,</hi> and all diſloyall treacherous Royaliſts) why caſt you not? I ſay, the Army may be caſt, and the Royaliſts remaine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, where are you then? when the whole kingdome (out of weakneſſe ſome, out of wickedneſſe other ſome, ſhall overwhelme you like an inundation or deluge, who ſhall then check them from giving you check-meat by plunderings and maſſacres, and what not? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>36. But theſe adverſe youngſters will politickly pretend, they only intend to ſtand on their guard, and to defend, not offend, and fooles like themſelves, think this is very faire, as foule as it is; but may it not be to ingratiate themſelves into the opinion of weaklings; why, they are honeſt men, defence is according to Nature, and Reaſons law: but may they not intend alſo by this to make us ſecure &amp; improvident on purpoſe to ſurprize us? may it not be to gain time to multiply their multitudes <hi>ad infinitum,</hi> and then over-power and finite us? Is it wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in warre to beleeve ſuggeſtions? Doth not Nature and reaſon teach us alſo to ſecure our ſelves? And how ſhall that be, but by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipating them at firſt, not ſuffering them to body or numerous it. The nature and malignity of their petition, the nature, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſition of the leaders and the led, ſhewes that their gliſtering pretenſes are not gold (though gilded) but lead; their words, expreſſions, and poſtures, ſhewes their intended proſtration of us, &amp;c. though we know alſo they will by theſe courſes proſtrate themſelves and their own in concluſion; who offends them, ſo, as ſuch offenſive defence need bee? Doth not their arming inforce arming? Doth not their univerſall violence (as they will have the King home <hi>fas aut nefas)</hi> import them virulent? and what may be preſaged from ſuch depraveds, but pravities? much more may be inferred from the contents of their diſcontented petition; ſo from the leaders and the led, ſo from their words, expreſſions, and poſtures; but comprehenſive underſtandings will ſave us the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and incomprehenſive or wilfull ones, will make us labour in vain, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>37. Laſtly, comes <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sinon,</hi> a ſlye fellow, a Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian traytor <hi>Scotes,</hi> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,—Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtiner. <hi>Idam,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sinon,</hi> or <hi>Scotos,</hi> the <hi>Scot,</hi> or the Clandeſtiner, he comes mouthing it, Breach of Covenant, breach of Covenant. It's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114919:8"/>
queried, In what? He bawles out, Oh <hi>Templum Domini, Templum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> Religion, the Kirk, Gods honour, worſhip, ſervice, ſuffer inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferables, Sects alſo muſt be diffected, and his King erected in his rights, &amp;c. and our State dejected, or elſe all is not right, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>38. But oh the hypocriticall villany of this cheating world, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, with the reſt aforeſaid, are made the Bawds to all villany; Oh ſhame to all ſuch Atheiſticall, inhumane, and barbarous Barbarians, for they care not for Religion nor the reſt, a ruſh, but as religious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars are conducing to their occults—their Clandeſtines, &amp;c. their ends are our endings and the beginnings of themſelves; it's plunder, the milk and the honey, and the cluſters of our Canaan Grapes they gape after; yet our fooles are foild with theſe follies, and herein alſo to truſt the truſtleſſe, with Life, Liberty, and Lands, on any tearmes, their ſecurity being onely a few—pious—pretenſes, which poſſeſſes with a ſecurity like to that of fooliſh <hi>Lakiſh,</hi> a retchleſſe Citie,—and ſo a Citie ſoon wrackt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>39. Well, well, wee have broken the Covenant about Religion, How trow? Why, we Presbyter it not? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nor ſhould wee as qualified, for it's contrary to Gods word, ſo to the covenant which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes the neareſt to Gods word, which Presbytery as quallified is not, as qualified it may, ſo we except againſt our excepters, and require their compliance, &amp;c. But doth the covenant allow to invade? and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo without covention or conviction? &amp;c. in what conventicle was this Doctrine forged, trow? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>40. Surely if the Covenant be ſtrictly ſeen into, we ſhall be forc'd to call our Clandeſtiner to an account, that we may ſee into <hi>Synon,</hi> or the <hi>Trojan</hi> horſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>41. His next reaſon of invaſion, is the Kings erection, &amp; our States dejection<hi>:</hi> That is, the <hi>Scots</hi> owne Kinging it over us, under pretence of the King,—a fine piece of gullery.</p>
            <p>42. Well, how proves the <hi>Scot</hi> we have broke this Covenant? oh well enough, well enough. Its ſo indeed, if his ill enough be well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Thus he proves it, we are to maintaine His Majeſtie in all his Might and Mightineſſe; Is not this proofe ſufficient? are wee not gone by this? Well, thus we yet recover our ſelves; Doth not the <hi>Scot</hi> deal Divel-like? For the Devill ſaith to Chriſt, <hi>caſt thy ſelfe downe;</hi> yet thou ſhalt not be caſt, for God hath promiſed that the Angels ſhall ſecure thee, &amp;c. But oh, Sir <hi>Sinon,</hi> Sathan leaves out (in his or thy wayes) So our Clandeſtiner (Devill-like) deviates the Kings High-way, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114919:8"/>
is,—as the King continues us in our Religion and Rights, &amp;c. How now Clandeſtiner, is this done? how is it then, we are undone? For what meanes all the yellings and bleatings over the Kingdome, &amp;c. Of infinites, for murthers, maſſacres, and undoings? &amp;c. How doth <hi>Synon,</hi> or our Senate, or our Synod: ſo our Citie, yea all the Cities and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in <hi>England;</hi> yea each Individuall anſwer this. I am at a ſtand, &amp;c. yet I will ſtand to it. Had the Covenant been abſolute, oh <hi>Scot,</hi> it had been ſo much the more deſolate, like thy ſelfe that urgeſt it. For to <note place="margin">Is not the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting to protect blood-ſhedders, blood-ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Covenanters &amp; protecters? ſure it is, or nothing is ſure. What had <hi>Saul</hi> done to loſe the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp;c. oh conſider,—can or doe his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites paralell our infinites. Are dumbe Divines of God? O pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitleſſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</note> covenant to protect him in all his greatneſſe, who by thy owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is guilty of infinites of blood-ſhed, I aske thee? What are inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall bloody, and knowing blood-ſhedders, and that of Infinites, contrary to oath and betruſt? are they not mighty Mrs and Trs? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve my weake judgement, and ſcrupilous conſcience, for ſo thou art bound in conſcience to doe. Did not the Prophets of old ſay, <hi>Thou art the man.</hi> And againe, <hi>thou haſt done fooliſhly; therefore the Lord</hi> (that is Juſtice) <hi>hath rent away thy Kingdome from thee.</hi> Thou <hi>David</hi> haſt ſlaine <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> &amp; drab'd his wife—retaliation ſhall retaliate, the ſword for the ſword, and thy ten Wives for his one, and that occulalry for thy occults, &amp;c. So ſhall juſtice alſo retaliate a <hi>Jezabel,</hi> though a Queene, for a <hi>Naboth,</hi> though a <hi>Naball.</hi> For <hi>as the Dogs lickt the blood of</hi> Naboth, <hi>ſo ſhall they that of</hi> Jezabel.</p>
            <p>43. To except againſt us for this quereing and alleadging Scripture to ſatisfie our ſcrupulous conſcience, is againſt Scripture and Religion, and ſo againſt God: and whats that but irreligion and atheiſme, and what are ſuch but ſuch, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>44. But our Covenant is firſt both in place and worth, alſo abſolute in rendring and in nature, for rights of Kingdome and Parliament; if conſcience you make as you urge and pretend, why then doe you ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionably invade the Rights of either, for the unrighteous? Your owne poſition as afore, the Kings guiltineſſe allowes not his erection to the proſtration of both States. Againe, the Kings ſupportment in his height and priviledges, are but reſpective, and ſo of no reſpect, if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited. Conſider, can reſpectives both in nature &amp; in rendring anſwer to abſolutes in both? being forfeited alſo as afore, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>45. Oh <hi>Engliſh,</hi> oh <hi>Scot,</hi> oh all ſorts, conſider, what fell on the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Nation for that their 12. Tribes did not call <hi>Saul</hi> to an accompt for ſome triviall wrong done to a paltry Pagan City; did not 3. yeares of famine fall on them, becauſe <hi>Sauls</hi> plottings for their deſtruction, and the blood he ſhed was not anſwered for. Sure <hi>Saul</hi> would not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114919:9"/>
himſelf; who then but the 12. Tribes ſhould have done it? which, cauſe they did not, they are puniſhed till <hi>Saul's</hi> 7. ſonnes, expiated for all, and ſo retaliated ſatisfaction in being hang'd up by the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> which City demanded Juſtice, and petitioned not for <hi>Sauls</hi> ſupportance againſt juſtice, much leſſe for his honor &amp; greatneſſe. Oh wiſe-headed <hi>Gibeonites,—</hi>oh fooliſh and giddi-brain'd <hi>Engliſh,</hi> oh depraved <hi>Scot,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>46. Thus much for Land men; let's now ſee if Sea-men have more wit, or more honeſty, ſo have any thing to ſay to this buſineſſe. Oh madneſſe, ther's nothing but weakneſſes or wickedneſſes in this world; for Sea-men ſay the ſame, and ſo Land and Sea and Aire, are I thinke nothing but aire. Well, I will land the Sea-men, and referre them for <note place="margin">We ſay as much for the Armie, if you will not helpe them for their own ſakes, yet help them for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſake, <hi>your King:</hi> if the end of Governours be King of all Governors.</note> what I have ſaid to the Land-men, and ſo let them goe. For I reſolve on brevity; for to ſay againe what I have ſaid, is to preſent you with Coleworts twice ſodde, only hints, the Reader cannot doe leſſe then comment. I conclude then, is it not madneſſe and folly, if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have offended you, or you are offended with it, you will (like <hi>Will: Somers)</hi> ſtrike who ever is next you. Is it not Treaſon to ſtrike at the Kingdome, which is the <hi>King King</hi> and yours? If you know it not, are you not weake? If you know, yet will not know, are you not wicked? Is it not a ſtriking againſt the Kingdom, not to ſtrike its ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, or to bring in it's Vice-roy to ſtrike and conquer it? but you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee, nor intend any ſuch thing; ah weakeneſſe, &amp;c. Your intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we know not, but your actions portend no leſſe; will you King the <hi>Vice-roy</hi> above the <hi>Roy?</hi> Is a people for a King, or a King for a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Whether is the meanes or the end King? whether is phyſicke or health King? If the Parlaiment have wrong'd you, right your ſelves in a faire way, ſo as you may not wrong the Kingdome, like a fooliſh fellow; who ſaith, the Mr. of the ſhip hath wronged him, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge himſelfe, will drowne the ſhip, that he may drown his Maſter, though withall he drowne himſelfe and all the reſt in it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>47. It may be I have ſuffered by the Parliament as much as any; what then? I will not <hi>(Will: Somers-like)</hi> ſtrike my next man or any, much leſſe <hi>my Lord and King the Kingdome;</hi> no, I will ſuffer againe and againe, yea to death, yea death it ſelfe, rather then endanger or be the death of <hi>my Lord.</hi> I ſcorn to Traytor or Rebell it ſo: ſo I will not oppoſe my wrongers, to the wronging of <hi>my Lord;</hi> yea I will helpe them to the righting of him, &amp;c. And if I cannot right my ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wronging <hi>my Lord,</hi> I will never be righted, yet count I am right, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114919:9"/>
48. Oh but ſome will newtralize it, and not take part with either, but defend againſt both; or if they offend any, it ſhall be the State who <note place="margin">Are not theſe Traitos to K. <hi>Salus?</hi>
               </note> have offended them, &amp;c. But are theſe ſayings for <hi>Seniors, for ſage, wiſe, and grave Governours,</hi> or for any? If you travell, and ſome of the formoſt of your company are ſet on by thieves and rogues, &amp;c. will you newtralize it? Are not thoſe Thieves and Murtherers that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not Thieves and Murtherers to their power? For by not helping, <hi>you helpe to rob and kill,</hi> the rob'd and kill'd, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>49. What if your Parents and Maſters, under whoſe roof you live, ſo owe duties to them anſwerably; If theſe were ſet on, will you newtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize alſo, and only ſefly defend? is not this murther and theft, as afore, if they miſcarry: ſo is it not treaſon in nature and reaſon to <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Pay maſters,</hi> or <hi>Maintainers,</hi> to whom you are engaged in all faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and loyalty, and ſo to leave them, will you to them turne Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alliſts and treacherous?</p>
            <p>50. Again, if they are conquered, are not you your ſelves conquered? they help you as well as themſelves: and doth not retaliation and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo duty and reaſon, ſay the ſame concerning you?</p>
            <p>51. Know you not oh weaklings, that you are more engaged to the Kingdome then any child or ſervant can be to his Father or Maſter; For parents and children are parted oft times you ſee <hi>to take the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes part,</hi> to part it from dangerous encounters.</p>
            <p>52. Sure, in a journey I will help my enemie, how then him who is not mine: but I am his, and maligne him I know not why nor where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for he hath done me no hurt, nor will, but much good, had I the goodneſſe to acknowledge it. Doth he not help me, and fight for mee, in fighting for himſelfe; yet for want of help may be conquered, and then the conqueſt of me is more probable and eaſie. Well foole, fight <note place="margin">The maligned Armie.</note> for thy enemie (if ſo) that's engaged on thy ſide, and ſide with him that he may be thy friend; fight then for thy friend, whoſe enemie thou art, &amp;c. that he may continue thy friend. But yet if thou beeſt ſo malicious, thou wilt not fight for either, fight yet with them, though not for them, yet for thy ſelfe and thy Father and Mr. in company, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>53. Thus fight with, or for Parliament and Armie, though they be <note place="margin">So the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> thy enemies, or thou art theirs, according to the premiſes, apply and ſave me the replication.—Fight with, or for them, as it conduceth to the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>54. But the Armie is a company of <hi>Sectaries, Independents,</hi> &amp;c. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou knoweſt not well what thou ſaiſt, if well and wiſely examined
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114919:10"/>
what a <hi>Sectariſt</hi> is<hi>:</hi> ſo, nor an <hi>Independent;</hi> nor will I now engage to <note place="margin">In the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates time they were pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, men of tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, &amp;c.—faithfull to death.</note> tell thee: but be it as thou ſaiſt, yet thou ſaiſt nothing to the purpoſe. Oh madneſſe; what's this to thee in this caſe? one hath thrown down <hi>Baals</hi> altar, Ergo, <hi>Gideon</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Joaſh</hi> muſt dye: but the wiſer <hi>Joaſh</hi> anſwered thoſe fooles, if <note n="*" place="margin">Shew <hi>Baals</hi> order, or leave your bauling,-ſhew us the ſame of God, &amp;c.—</note> 
               <hi>Baal</hi> be a God, and be offended, hee will right himſelfe. Sure if the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Turk were faithfull to our State, and would fight to deliver it, I would fight with him <note n="a" place="margin">Sectariſts &amp; Independents ſo cal'd, have ſaved the king dome &amp; City, for none elſe would, &amp;c.</note> and for him: and owe we not him alſo thankes, honour, and reward? Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent religions, nor irreligion, quit not humanitie and juſtice.</p>
            <p>God by <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. enjoynes them to be <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> till convinced, <hi>and joyes in it, if in ſincerity;</hi> ſee and be ſatisfied. <hi>Why condemneſt and judgeſt thou him</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Let each one be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,—note it in his owne,-not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.—If the doubter be damn'd,-force not the doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, leſt thou damne him &amp; thy ſelfe. Is it nothing to condemne &amp; damn?</note>? he is Gods ſervant, <hi>not thine;</hi> Thou ſhalt not anſwer for him, therefore be anſwered: and ſuffer him to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent</hi> it, as well as he thee to <hi>Presbyter it,</hi> is it not juſt? <hi>Thou unjuſt one,</hi> who denies him this liberty?—yet wilt licentiate, &amp;c. Promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors againſt fundamentals, I am againſt:—but yet reſervedly,<hi>—to hold, none can with-hold:</hi> ſo I am againſt prophaners and blaſphemers! what wouldſt thou more? Know weaklings, know <hi>that the beauty of ſincerity and juſtice, love, peace, and humanity; though accompanied with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Religion,</hi> not againſt: ſo alſo with many occular deformities and ſeeming giddineſſes, and fooleries<hi>—are preferrable before a forced and ignorant Claſſicke, beauty, and order, &amp;c.</hi> without ſincerity or any the reſt aforeſaid, &amp;c.—why—art thou againſt—what God is for?</p>
            <p>55. But are not ſuch Royalliſts, ſo, all ſorts under what notion ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Traitors, Murtherers, thieves, &amp;c. <hi>that fight againſt themſelves and their poſterities,</hi> and againſt the Kingdome, <hi>their Soveraign, &amp;c.</hi> under pretence, as for <hi>its Steward,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c. Doth not ſhame and infamy attend them, beſides baſe ſlavery? to them and theirs, &amp;c. And though you be offended at the Parliament; yet why againſt your ſelves and yours, and the Kingdom? and yet why alſo againſt the Parliament? you ſay they have taken your eſtates, &amp;c.—Oh fooles, have you neither witt nor honeſty to reaſon wiſely and rightly? Foole know, they act but ſecondarily, alſo <hi>juſtly and inforcedly;</hi> Is it not <hi>the King and your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">This is ſpoken only to Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants who have forfeited all.</note> 
               <hi>ſelves</hi> by the Scots owne ſayings, (for all they ſeeme to ſtand ſo for the King) who have plundered you of your eſtates <hi>by turns,</hi> and now you would turne it upon the State. Why charge you not the King <hi>as doe his owne Countreymen?</hi> Doth not the scot charge him as the <hi>Originall cauſe</hi> of all the blood ſhed, &amp;c. <hi>in the</hi> 3. <hi>Nations,</hi> know its <hi>a Nation of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> thus charge him, diſcharge him if thou canſt. If hee be <hi>the firſt</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114919:10"/>
               <hi>cauſe,</hi> thou art <hi>the ſecond,</hi> for ſeconding him againſt <hi>hoth States,</hi> the large and contract, <hi>Kingdome and Parliament:—</hi>ſo the Parliament: juſtly for thy treachery <hi>to the whole,</hi> and in behalfe of it, did force from <note n="*" place="margin">Shall a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn the Judge or Executioner for taking life or eſtate? whereas him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demner &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioner of himſelfe by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> thee but part of thy eſtate, to helpe to ſecure <hi>what thou wouldſt have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traid;</hi> whereas thou haſt forfeited all, <hi>yea, life alſo.</hi> Foole, or Knave, or both, art thou not engag'd to them for thy life, and the remainder of thy eſtate, all being at their command (conſidering how forfeited) in behalfe of the Kingdome <hi>thy Soveraign?</hi> Learne wiſdome and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty hence-forward to acknowledge what's right, and their goodneſſe to one <hi>ſo unrighteous,</hi> and make amends for future, by dedicating thy life and eſtate to the State, <hi>for the State, &amp;c.</hi> Fight againſt the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, yea all Stewards <hi>for thy Soveraigne,</hi> the Kingdome, <hi>thy King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>56. But many are deſperate; for the Parliament (as they ſay) hath abuſed them, and oppreſt them more then ever the King did, and they are as very ſlaves under them, as the King can make them,—and yet they have been as faithfull and deſerving of the Parliament as can be; having ventured limbes, life, liberty &amp; eſtate,—alſo, ſuch and ſo much wages is due to them, but not a penny can they get, though they, <hi>ſo their wives and children are ready to famiſh;</hi> alſo they are contemned, ſlighted, &amp; villified, &amp;c. If it be ſo as afore, its a hard and urging caſe, &amp;c. For men are but men, <hi>not Gods,</hi> &amp;c. It becomes not the fountain of Juſtice to ſend out ſuch <hi>foule ſtreames;</hi> nor to be the cauſe of <hi>ſuch floods of teares,</hi> nor of rending and tearing complaints, &amp;c. Yet here anſwer thee, as at <hi>Sect.</hi> 47. whether repaire for ſatisfaction,—and implore them to doe as they would be done by.</p>
            <p>58. If the riſing of the people be not from ſome of the grounds fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. <note place="margin">Quaere.</note> As firſt, The licentiat reading of lying Ballets and books to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame the State and the Armie, and ſo to incenſe the people againſt both—alſo to divide the people amongſt themſelves,—which is moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous—in ſo famous a Citiie, to ſuffer ſuch inſufferables,—and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, as if they fided with ſuch baſe ones—againſt both States—which is not only great weakneſſe, but wickedneſſe alſo,—may they be accepted for Protecters of Parliament and Kingdom,—which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate both as afore?</p>
            <p>Another thing that befooles the people—and ſo cauſe them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o riſe againſt—Parliament and Armie—yea themſelves and theirs is, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <hi>of the Kings ſtate,</hi> degree and condition, &amp;c. and <hi>an opinion of him beyond what is, &amp;c.</hi> which we intend to reſolve by Quaeries in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; only one or two inſtances here, &amp;c.—under the notion <hi>(King)</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114919:11"/>
and other titles of <hi>ſacred Majeſtie, &amp;c.—</hi>They are beſotted to an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrizing, <hi>as if rahter a God then a man.—</hi>Alſo as if all were his own <hi>ſelfely—</hi>cauſe <hi>King</hi> relates not, as doth Steward, <hi>which ſends to a Lord;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See ſect. 46. where the end of Kings is K. as juſtice, ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, peace, &amp;c. of the people, &amp;c.</note> whereas all his <hi>Titles, Glories, Crowne, Throne, Scepter, &amp;c.—</hi>are the States at large, and his only by way of <hi>ſteward-ſhip</hi> and <hi>Deputi-ſhip;</hi> As are the <hi>Sword, Cap of Maintenance,</hi> ſo traine of Officers, <hi>the Cities, not the Majors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ignorance, crafty knaves (eſpecially depraved Clergy-men, and men of loſt fortunes make uſe of, to incite the people for their own ends, as at <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. and 8.—But our loyalty to our <hi>Lord Salus</hi> enjoyns a plaine diſcovery of all particulars concerning him, to prevent (if it were poſſible) murthers, maſſacres, &amp;c.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere,</hi> if it be not treachery, <hi>not to treat hereof?</hi> or to intreate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe <note place="margin">Quaere.</note> 
               <hi>the intreater thereof,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Parliament and peoples rights alſo are not known, <hi>which clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> would cleere all, &amp;c. <hi>and make all cleere up, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſſures from Parliament (as ſaid to be) incite alſo, ſo want of juſtice, &amp;c. the remedies known, <hi>the cure may be eaſie,</hi> if care be.</p>
            <p>The bounds of obedience, ſo of Treaſon and rebellion (not by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe law only, but) by law rationall and ſo binding, <hi>are not knowns,</hi> and ſo the ignorant are bound to their good behaviour againſt all good behaviour, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>59. Is this or that <hi>treaſon, &amp;c.</hi> againſt the K. <hi>Steward of the kingdom,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Queries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: ſo of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</note> 
               <hi>as ſelfly conſidered?</hi> (ſo much in every mans mouth) or not rather, as hee relates to <hi>the State at large,</hi> his Lord, ſo it's for <hi>his Lords ſake,</hi> not his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere</hi> alſo, If it be not as he continues <hi>in his ſphear of government,</hi> or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaere.</hi> The State at large.</note> rather in the execution of government, <hi>according to the will of his* Lord</hi> expreſt in his Lawes,—ſo in all faithfulneſſe to him, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere.—If out of his ſpheare he be not a privat man,</hi> &amp;c. ſo not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but reſiſtable, &amp;c. St. <hi>Paul, I knew him not to bee Gods high Prieſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quaere.</note> Why? Becauſe his actions were below his place as a Judge. Ignorant he could not be, that he was the high Prieſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>60. If to raiſe Armes <hi>againſt the kingdomes Army,</hi> the Kingdome <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King,</hi> by Sect. 46. <hi>if it be not treaſon?</hi> the ſaid Army continuing <note place="margin">Quaere.</note> faithfull to the kingdome, in its defence, is it not to take up Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the kingdome itſelfe?</p>
            <p>61. If an abuſing the Army, it continuing faithfull before, be not an affront to the Kingdome which is King?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114919:11"/>
62. If newtralizing, that is, not helping, ſiding, and taking part <note place="margin">Quaere.</note> with the Army againſt the Kingdomes enemies, <hi>be not treaſon to the kingdome?</hi> how then to take part againſt it? to ſuppreſſe or enſlave it, by raiſing Forces of their own Faction, to keep it under,—or to leave the Kingdom naked to ſelf inſurrections, or forraign invaſions, &amp;c.—alſo to have brought the King forcibly home, to have born out, and coloured all their deſignes, &amp;c—inforcings,—&amp;c.</p>
            <p>If it be not lawfull to make the foreſaid <hi>quaeries,</hi> and the like, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quaere.</note> 
               <hi>querelous inquiſitions and exceptions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>63. Oh thou Citie of <hi>London,</hi> ſo all the Cities and Countries of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Application.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea each individual man therein, read reaſon, and call to mind, as thus, Theſe Rakeſhames that pretend the King, <hi>intend themſelves,</hi> and are the ſame that fought againſt us as afore, to <hi>inſlave us,</hi> and we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them for our liberties, &amp;c. why expended wee our blood and meanes? What, to yeeld and entertain them at the laſt? Much better might we have yeelded at firſt, and ſpared all, then now at the laſt;—ſeeing alſo by our affronts, <hi>their revenge is aggravated to the uttermoſt,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the nullifying our Religion, and enforcing upon us a Regiment, or imperious government under its name; ſo our lives, liberties, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates are gone, and we are in their hands <hi>like Rogues and Gally-ſlaves.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">King of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland—&amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fools—fools—the wiſe have eyes.—Lord Mayor of London—&amp;c. Are they any any more then Titles?—Is not each ones life, land, liberty, and eſtate his owne by Law and Nature? Its onely the higheſt Title of honour allowed by the State,—So Prince of Wales, Earle of Eſſex, &amp;c.</note> As for the King we now underſtand our ſelves better then before, he is by Sect. 58. <hi>the kingdomes Steward,</hi> the peoples and kingdomes wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, (as the end of Kings and all Governours) is <hi>Lord and King.</hi> He hath alſo forfeited all <hi>by his faithleſneſſe to his Lord—</hi>he is to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as is the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> to the Citie, and no more, <hi>chiefe Deputie Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours both of them,</hi> yet not by any ſelfneſſe, but as in favour conferred on, by and for the State, <hi>the Citie.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">The Lord Mayor is by <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x</hi> King of the City, in reſpect of all ſubordinate Rulers: 32 Kings, that is, <hi>Lieutenant Governours of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties, Joſhua</hi> conquered on this ſide Jordan. May the Mayor take up Armes againſt the Citie, or rob them by Sea or Land, or <hi>rebell and traytor them,</hi> or burn their houſes? &amp;c. And muſt the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens for all that, petition, intreat, and treat with their abuſive treacherous ſervant? &amp;c. Is not the Mayor a traytor, a rebell, for ſo doing? Apply them, &amp;c. <hi>Rex.</hi> is Ruler, not King—So by <hi>Rex</hi> all are Kings, or none are—&amp;c. It's falſly tranſlated <hi>Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or applied onely to one more then another: the word will not beare any thing but <hi>Ruler,</hi> yet that will hardly be rul'd; nor will the Hebrew or Greek beare the tranſlation <hi>(King)</hi> at all, &amp;c. Why then to theſe more then others? Ruler is alſo unruly,—ſo not right, as too ſelfly<hi>—Steward ſends to a Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> May the Mayor maſter the Citie? will the Citizens ſide with him againſt themſelves?—hath hee any commiſſion to kill, rob, rape? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114919:12"/>
As for the Parliament and Army, if they have wronged us, yet will not we wrong <hi>the kingdome</hi> to right our ſelves of them,—but let's help them all we can; if not for themſelves, yet for our ſelves, ſo ours, &amp;c. Yet, why not the Army for themſelves alſo, ſeeing they have done us no hurt? Newtrality will nullifie us in our Religion, Liberties and Lives; we have experience of their truſtineſſe: and we have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (except we want ſence) of the perfidiouſneſſe and treachery of the <hi>other Armies,</hi> they are genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly Atheiſts, their commanders men of no Religion, onely politick pretenders to deceive: their actions and deſignes define them as afore.—As for the <hi>Army</hi> if <hi>Sectaries,</hi> if <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, &amp;c.</hi> yet we know not well, <hi>if ſo,</hi> becauſe the true definition of either is not agreed on. However, what is it to us? If faithfull to us and the State, it's to God, not to us. They ſuffer us to <hi>Presbyter it;</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice requires, we ſuffer them to <hi>Independent it.</hi> Deſtroyers of Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, ſo Blaſphemers, they allow not of, often declared by them—Thus qualified, how is it we allow not of, them? ſeeing God himſelfe doth, by <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. Well, let's weigh all aforeſaid, and let's immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſend them all the help we can, if not for their ſakes, yet for our own, and ours, and the Kingdomes, to ſet a period to theſe troubles, &amp;c. For if the adverſe Army have the better, we have the worſt of it. We are politickly called <hi>Fomenters of Warre:</hi> we muſt be wiſe, and not feare words, we muſt <hi>foment,</hi> (if <hi>foment</hi> they call it) that is, we muſt ſtir up and ſecond defenſively, againſt ſuch offenders, who would ſurprize us, by preventing reſiſtance; by ſuch aſperſions they foment all they can, by raiſing the Countries, to raiſe them, to the Countries razing. If we foment not <hi>juſt defence</hi> againſt their <hi>unjuſt offence,</hi> we are great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, let's not traytor it to our King the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> nor to the Parliament, nor the Army, wherein they continue faithfull, &amp;c. ſo nor to our ſelves, nor ours: but now before we part, <hi>reſolve, to diſſolve</hi> theſe fomenters, theſe <hi>Achans,</hi> theſe <hi>troubles of Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> And let's learn to beare (till we know how to help it) leſſer injuries from Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army, if ſo' rather then <hi>the great,</hi> intollerable, the <hi>inexpreſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> from the other ſide, &amp;c. and conſider, and doe not we our ſelves foment our own miſeries? there was likelihood of a period before this, but we cry out of Parliament and Army, for not ſetling the kingdom, and that they doe nothing thus long, when as we our ſelves breed and <note n="*" place="margin">In that Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us in plotting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the State, the Army and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, ſo called,—and inviting in the Scots—alſo fiding it with the <hi>Roy</hi> and his <hi>Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> &amp;c. - Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to <hi>force home the King,</hi> under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a <hi>Treaty.</hi>
               </note> increaſe new work, new troubles to them and our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Oh State Repreſentative,</hi> a word or two to you, and I have
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114919:12"/>
done, onely to minde and hint you, <hi>for more (ſure) I need not doe,</hi> if you be noble minded, generous and genuine; but if contrary, as ignoble, &amp;c. What ſhall be done to ſet you right? I tax not, but <hi>preventively cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Remember the univerſall, naturall, rationall precept, <hi>Doe as you would be done to, &amp;c.</hi> Is not this enough to Naturaliſts, Moraliſts, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles? How then, <hi>if Chriſtianity be added?</hi> Shall it adde nothing? <hi>If deducted,</hi> leſſe you cannot be, and be men, &amp;c. <hi>Statues</hi> you may be, but not <hi>Statute-makers—</hi>except as afore.—Would you be abuſed, or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherized with <hi>in the leaſt of your truſts?</hi> Surely no; <hi>then doe not ſo;</hi> Would you not <hi>traytor</hi> and <hi>skellom,</hi> and <hi>baſe fellow,</hi> that fellow that ſhould ſo abuſe you in the meaneſt betruſt? &amp;c. If ſo, inferre, <note n="*" place="margin">Which you may loſe in a moment, cauſe you are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary. Alſo, are they of moment, like your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, fame, ſo the love and welfare of your friends and poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, &amp; your quitting them from ſlavery? Conſider, &amp;c.</note> what's due in juſt retaliation for failing in the greateſt betruſts mortality is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of? as of Life, Livelihood, Liberties and Religion, &amp;c. See to it, O ſee to it, <hi>I ſpeak onely to the guilty,</hi> if any be: blemiſh not, nor beſpot your Honours—by treacherous aſperſions, &amp;c. though many be laid upon you, never the like on any Parliament before, and that without controll—or commination, yet let it not be juſtly. Remember the love of the people in chuſing you, ſo of their great hopes and joy in your faithfulnes; forfeit them not, we intreat you, but free your free chooſers, <hi>ſo all your friends,</hi> ſo your own poſterities, that they may bleſſe you in future times, and your names and remembrances <hi>may be famous for ever;</hi> elſe, infamy for ever attends you: ſo <hi>the cryes and curſes</hi> of your chooſers, ſo of your children and poſterities, ſo of all your friends and kindred, yea of the whole kingdome or people <hi>your true King,</hi> who made you what you are, and commiſſioned you, &amp;c. but not to commit them, &amp;c. On beſlave not, nor vaſſalage <hi>your Lords,</hi> to any <hi>their Stewards.</hi> Conſider and digeſt what I ſay, and digreſſe not, &amp;c.—</p>
            <p>O let not any inſinuations, flatteries, hopes, promiſes, <note n="*" place="margin">Or in your power to keep, as to give, &amp;c. <hi>I adde to the aforeſaid cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> nor let envy, hate, malice, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge—to—or againſt any,—hurt the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> quit thy ſelf if thou canſt, if not, reſerve it till thou canſt not offend.</note> prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or diſhonorable honours circumvent you, and ſo beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and jeering from your circumventers. Is there any thing ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and cheering, as a cleare conſcience, even as a moraliſt, &amp;c. None can give you, or preferre you, but you muſt firſt inable them by giving to, and preferring them; reſerve rather then give to ſuch, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive againe, and ſo to be beholden, and give thankes for what's your *own. But what are ſuch givers and receivers—alſo—receivers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, from ſuch; given to, givers? &amp;c.—of what alſo is neither the givers nor receivers own but <hi>their Lords,</hi> the Kingdomes, <hi>their King?</hi> What I ſay, are ſuch, &amp;c. &amp;c. but &amp;c.—Oh conſider, conſider, &amp;c. and comply to juſtice, equity, and all honorable things. Honour your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114919:13"/>
ſelves by your wiſdomes and fidelity, as you have done, which preferre <hi>as more noble,</hi> and withall immortall, in that it ſhall live when you are dead—before all other baſe and by-ends—which ſhall when you are gone, <hi>infamous you;</hi> and leave a baſe and ſordid ſtench of you, to all eternity, &amp;c.—Give forraigne States cauſe to honour you, and make not your ſelves a jeering ſtock to the whole world, till it come to a proverb, <hi>As ill as an Engliſhman,—as baſe as a Britain, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How wiſely and ably did the Holland State quit themſelves of their <hi>Tyrannous King,</hi> &amp; continue faithfull to the people <hi>that followed them,</hi> and govern them with peace and love, cauſe with <hi>juſtice, protection and ſafety?</hi> Sure the ſame wayes would have had the ſame effects with us. What ſhall I ſay? <hi>It's with the lateſt,</hi> but not too late, if this you will do. Inform the people aright of their <hi>own rights, yours and their Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royes,</hi> when at the righteſt,—alſo as now, <hi>poſtur'd, qualified, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned with all kind of wrong doings,</hi> to a moſt righteous people to him; <hi>Why ſpare you, or feare you to ſpeak?</hi> May, yea, doth it not betray us? If we have, doe, and muſt venture our lives, <hi>what is't</hi> (if juſt and right, and withall conducing) <hi>ſhall ſilence us?</hi> Had <hi>Heſter</hi> been ſilent, <hi>where</hi> 
               <note place="margin">O let not one woman put down ſo many men for cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, &amp;c. being alſo not ſo engaged as are you.</note> 
               <hi>bad ſhe and hers been?</hi> You have fought againſt, and dare you not ſpeak, nor give way to ſpeak againſt, <hi>in what's juſt,—</hi>alſo when it is for the Kingdome and the people, &amp;c. Conducingly, give way, and you ſhall finde men will ſpeak out. Juſtice and your ingagements, the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes welfare,</hi> and <hi>to prevent its illfare,</hi> claimes this at your hands, and we dare, however, <hi>quaere,</hi> if it be not treachery to the Kingdome, the people in generall <hi>(our Generall</hi> or <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c.) Not to allow the exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting of the aforeſaids, <hi>as conducing to their delivery, &amp;c. the children are come to the birth,</hi> give ſtrength to bring forth? Now we have done, and deliver up what is ſaid, with our ſelves, to the judgement of the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous. And the bleſſing of God be with you, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DIXI.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:114919:13"/>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcripts.</head>
            <p>THis Book lying by me ſome time after it was written (by reaſon of ſome hinderances) it hath now furthered it ſelfe with the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome ſecond thoughts, I hope very conducing as to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,—ſo to particulars, &amp;c.—</p>
            <p>Is not treaſon, the betraying of juſt truſts and ingagements? Is not <note place="margin">Quaere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Of Treaſons.</note> that of a Kingdome the greateſt truſt? Are not all ſorts ingaged to the Kingdome, before the Steward, or any? Nay, are they ingaged to the Steward <hi>at all,</hi> but for the Kingdomes ſake? And is not their failing it alone (how then in ſiding with the Steward, or any againſt it) <hi>the greateſt treaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is it then in the Steward moſt ingaged <hi>by oath, betruſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance,</hi> not onely to faile or neglect, but to endeavour his uttermoſt <hi>againſt his Lord</hi> in the higheſt degree?</p>
            <p>Falſe Truſts, Oathes, &amp;c. to faile for true and juſt ones, is not trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but faithfulneſſe and juſtice,—as, to faile the Steward in behalfe <hi>of his Lord.—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be not treaſon to preferre any ſelfe-end, or any one, <hi>as the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quaere.</note> 
               <hi>called King,</hi> or his ſonnes called <hi>Prince or Duke,</hi> or any one, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing whatſoever, yea though it be Religion, Gods worſhip, or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as cal'd, or indeed, &amp;c. before the generall good, to its ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,—cauſe <hi>it's King and Soveraigne,</hi> and God himſelfe preferres it before the aforeſaids,—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>I will have mercy before Sacrifice, &amp;c.—</hi>the Sabbath is for man,—in humanities, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Traytors (however ſmiled on) are ſmit with contempt as the baſeſt of men, and are not truſted of their Truſters, but in caſes of neceſſity, and that with much feare and jealouſie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>See to this all ſorts, from the the Throne to Threſhold,—it imbaſeth the beſt: See to it, I ſay, Parliaments, Kings, Princes, Peers, Prieſts, &amp;c. the corruption of the beſt is worſt of all.</p>
            <p>66. Oathes, Covenants, &amp;c. in behalf of the Steward, <hi>againſt his Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Of Oathes, Covenants, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>the kingdome,</hi> binds not, all ſorts are bound to breake them, except
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114919:14"/>
they will bind themſelves to be Traytors, Murtherers, and Theeves.</p>
            <p>67. Rebellion is to reſiſt juſt Governours in their juſt Governments, <note place="margin">Rebellion.</note> diſobedience is the ſame: elſe it's none.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>
               </label> If the moſt ingaged Governours, or Stewards, that affront <hi>their Lords Salus, and his Lawes,</hi> and their ends of Government, Juſtice, and Protection, be not the greateſt Rebels?—Oft-times they <hi>rebell</hi> firſt and moſt, and yet tax the faithfull to their Lord, for <hi>Rebels,</hi> cauſe they ſide not with them in their rebellion <hi>againſt their Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will the <hi>Steward</hi> urge his <hi>Lords</hi> ſervants to keep falſe Oathes and Truſts to him <hi>againſt his Lord,</hi> and yet hee makes no reckoning of true ones? Sure he, by unjuſtly accuſing of them, he juſtly accuſeth himſelfe much more.</p>
            <p>68. Murther is without juſt cauſe to kil, or nor to ſave if we can—what <note place="margin">Murther.</note> is it then in the <hi>moſt ingaged Stewards</hi> to ſave and protect—yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily to murther, or endevour the <hi>murthering of their Lord Salus,</hi> and his faithfull ſervants,—cauſe they will not ſide with them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>their Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is't alſo in the ſervants that ſide with them againſt their Lord to ruinate him,—ſo his faithfull ſervants, is it not murther as well as treaſon?</p>
            <p>The juſtly inforc'd <hi>to kill,</hi> either in defence of <hi>their Lord Salus,</hi> or of themſelves, though they kill, I ſay,—yet they murther not, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>69. Hath the ſame definition or bounds that murther hath, <hi>the unjust</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Theft &amp; Robbery, Of Warre.</note> 
               <hi>ſides taking</hi> is theft, the other is none.</p>
            <p>The name and countenance of warre quits not, nor qualifies it from murther and theft on the unjuſt ſide,—it aggravates rather by its continuance—and violent perpetrations,—alſo as done with defiance, and a high hand, openly, &amp;c. as if juſtifiable, as alſo by the Steward againſt his Lord, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>
               </label> 70. See to the aforeſaid definitions of Treaſon, Murther, Theft, and Rebellion, &amp;c. all ſorts,—both States, the King, Princes, &amp; Dukes, ſo cal'd, yea Peers—Prieſts, and Prelats.—So all Countries and Cities, &amp;c. <note place="margin">Names. Titles, &amp;c. of Kings, Princes, etc. with the reſt, alter not natures:—but ingagements make the aforeſaids more unnaturall and greater Treaſons, Thefts, Murthers, &amp;c.</note> yea, each individuall, and apply as cauſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and for future,—let it leſſen thee to leſſen the aforeſaid offenders, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> 71. Well, but the King wrong'd them not, as hath done, and doth the Parliament, nor can they be greater ſlaves to the King, then <note place="margin">Object.</note> the Parliament makes of them,—&amp;c.—by impriſonment, by plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and contempts, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114919:14"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> I anſwer, If it be the objection of Malignants and Royaliſts, ſee then in part to Sect. 55. in ſpeciall,—in generall to 47. <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> If it be the good deſerving and faithfull party that complains— ſee to Sect. 56. ſo 47. and for full ſatisfaction as followeth. <note place="margin">Yet all ſorts by the Scots poſition, may charge their ſufferings originally on the King.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Each one forgets what the King did, ſo what they are freed from,— being onely taken up with their preſent ſufferings, of which they are moſt ſenſible,—alſo they minde not, or call not to minde what the King intended to doe,—the which I hope when I have minded them of, they will be of another minde, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> Haſt thou forgot the infinite Monopolies, as of Sope, Tobacco,— Pins, Leather, Wines, &amp;c. and indeed what not,—alſo the ten ſhillings <note place="margin">Scarce any commodity exempted, &amp; all in time would have come under the Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts. But all this is forgot.</note> a peece for the needleſſe freedome, called <hi>the new Corporation,</hi> &amp;c. and the reſt of which were coming on <hi>ad infinitum.—</hi>And amongſt the reſt <hi>Pole and Ship-money</hi> as Capitals? Was it nothing to quit thee of the charge, attendance, trouble and vexation, &amp;c. one way or other, to an undoing thee in thy eſtate, and in the peace of thy minde, &amp;c. By the Staring Star-chamber, and the High-Commiſſion, &amp;c. What ſayſt thou to the vexations ſuits, troubles, and attendance at <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> twixt the Parſon and thy perſon, about trivials,—as Holy-dayes keeping, or not,—beſides infinites more, which I need not ſtand to name.</p>
            <p>Did not the Court of Wards keep watch and ward over thee? Now thou mayſt doe as much by it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou forgot the <hi>German Horſemen,</hi> projected for thy projection and perpetuall inſlavement, and not for a preſent defence, as are ours. The <hi>Spaniſh Navy</hi> had the ſame intention, and had done the deed, if <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> All theſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally,—not inforc't there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Hurrying it in the popular ſtreets in their popular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots &amp; ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</note> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had not undone it, &amp;c.—Privy-Seales for money,-and the priſon for non-payment thereof, oppreſt the able and rich cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly,—&amp;c. And all theſe not for thy juſt and neceſſitated defence, but for thy offence, as on purpoſe to raiſe a ſtock, a <hi>Magazine of money &amp; means</hi> from thy ſelf, to provide <hi>Scorpions</hi> to whip thee. So manicles and Fetters for a Turkiſh inſlavement, alſo to ſupport (him that ſhould be) thy protector, in all <hi>Revellings, Maskings, Pleaſures, Playes</hi> and <hi>Delights,</hi> &amp;c. by the ruine of thee and thine,—whilſt thou and thine thus op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, are pining and languiſhing with griefe and preſſures, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> Now for the Parliament, let's ſee what they have done to thee:— admit much amiſſe, yet beleeve the <hi>Scots</hi> in this, that the King (the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114919:15"/>
Kingdomes Steward) is cauſe of all: for if he had not done the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids, theſe after neceſſitated doings by them had never been done—So when thou accuſeſt them, thou doſt implicitly accuſe the accuſer and miſuſer of them and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as the originall cauſe of all.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> Is It not the aforeſaid doings of his—by the Scots own ſaying—that hath been the cauſe of all theſe <hi>Warres, Bloodſhed, Loſſe of Eſtates, Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olland</hi> payes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xciſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception</note> 
               <hi>loſſe of trade,—</hi>So exciſe, &amp;c. that thou ſo excepteſt againſt?</p>
            <p>Lay it then where it ſhould be, and not upon the immediate occular, inſtrumentall, inforced Afflicters of thee,—to whom no queſtion its an affliction, thus to afflict thee, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> Is not thy Lawyer, Councellor, and Atturney inforc'd oft-times to undoe thee with charges and expences againſt thy offending adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? who will have the Cloak from thy back, and next thy ſuit, yea thy <note place="margin">The ſpirited man chuſeth to yeeld to this, rather then to his—inſulting ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary.</note> ſhirt, and ſo ſtrip thee to nakedneſſe if thou defendeſt not,—another keeps back, or layes claime to thy Land, and eſtate, and will unſtate thee, if thou defendeſt not.—Yea alſo it may be, though thou defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt,—his might will out-right thee, and the expences may exceed the principall, that it had been better to have yeelded at firſt.—But who knowes the iſſue of things? It may be thou mighteſt on eaſie tearmes have recovered all, of others, then, others have done ſo.—Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures muſt be adventured on, or elſe we muſt give up our rights, as our Cloakes and Clothes, &amp;c. to each unrighteous challenger, which no ſpirited man can yeeld to.—Adventure we not our lives, and all wee have, on darings, challenges, and abuſes, rather then be out-braved and inſulted over? A ſtomackfull reſiſtance and defence is an honor, and it oft prevents offences, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Thus by the Scots own ſaying, the Kings offence hath inforced the Parliaments and thy defence; and that defence, theſe expences, preſſures, and undoings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> But thou wilt yet ſay, the Parliament hath oppreſt and abuſed thee beyond a juſt and neceſſitated defence;—Be it ſo, this yet juſtifies not thy unfaithfulneſſe to <hi>thy Lord the Kingdome,</hi> if his Stewards contrary to his will (who provided them for thy protection, and to doe thee ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) abuſe thee,—right thy ſelfe of the Steward as thou canſt, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wronging thy Lord;—</hi>ſee for further ſatisfaction at Sect. 47.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> But oh you fountaines of juſtice,—let your honours, your fames,— and your names be more precious, and blemiſh them not by ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, but for this; ſee in full at <hi>Sect.</hi> 64. 56. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> But now laſt of all, I have met with a liſt of their extravagancies, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114919:15"/>
&amp;c. as <hi>great offices, places, incomes, &amp;c.—</hi>as Colonels in the Warre,—keepers of <hi>Townes, Cities, Caſtles,—Houſes, Parkes,</hi> and <hi>Forreſts:—</hi>Alſo great advancements by Biſhops Lands,—and laſtly by depraved <hi>injuſtice, oppreſſion, corruption,</hi> and <hi>bribery, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe laſt are juſtly exceptable againſt, <hi>if high and heinous, &amp;c.—</hi>Trivials muſt not be too much preſt—or cenſured:—thou canſt not Angelize men. <hi>David—that man of men—</hi>bid<hi>—Mephiboſheth—</hi>and <hi>Ziba</hi> divide the Land,—whereas the whole was <hi>Mephiboſheths, &amp;c.—</hi>But let's examine the other;—which before I doe, I will place thee (their accuſer) in their places,—cauſe by reflection—thy accuſation will be the better judged of, &amp;c.—Lets now ſee how thou canſt come off, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> Admit the Offices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> places—before-named, ſo the keeping of <hi>Caſtles, Townes, Towrs and Forts,—</hi>were in thy diſpoſure by—conſent of the Kingdome—as—are many places in the hands of each <hi>Lord Major,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">By cuſtome and conſent of the City.</note>—&amp;c.—but in ſpeciall in the hands of <hi>the King,</hi> when time was,—its not then—a power uſurp'd ſo farre as confer'd—by conſent, by way of betruſt—&amp;c.—Doth not nature—and reaſon <hi>firſt accommodate ones ſelf—and theirs—</hi>as neareſt, before remotes—provided they ſupply thoſe places with<hi>—perſons—faithfull,</hi> and each way fitting.—If this they faile of, they are faulty,—for they ought prefer the univerſall, in juſtice,—ſafety,—and rights,—before ſelfe-ends that are not right.—Said not <hi>Solomon</hi> to his <hi>Queene, thou ſhalt have ſonnes to make Rulers over all Lands?—</hi>Did not <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> make their ſonnes <hi>Prieſts—</hi>and <hi>Judges,—</hi>and they might—had they beene right; why ſhould not honour—pleaſure—and profit—be theirs, ſeeing confer'd on them (provided univerſally improv'd) as upon, or to others.—Who is't, that having—friends,—kindred, or children,—would not doe the like?—as—for the adventurous and faithfull in the Wars,—they are worthy of it,—ſo are the States, if they—would improve themſelves worthy for the univerſall.—Is not his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax—</hi>ſo Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell—</hi>worthy of their confer'd honours—and remembrances?—Nature, reaſon,—juſtice,—and policy of State, enjoyne honours—and rewards—to all deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, <note place="margin">Men are men, and need en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, &amp;c.</note>—and the State as Judges ought to conſider of it, and performe accordingly to all,—and I would they did;—no State, no Prince, but does, will, may, yea ought to doe it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> But what if we now parallell <hi>or diſcrimen the Parliaments and Kings actions? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114919:16"/>
            <p>Thoſe of the King—what he did,—and that not of neceſſity, &amp;c.—<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> Went he not againſt <hi>Scotl.</hi> with force to have ſetled E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, &amp;c.</note> but of a high hand—and with intention, &amp;c.—projecting the utter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlavement of the people or Kingdome,—and to have alſo—ruined Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,—and only allowed <hi>ſome Complements and Ceremonials,</hi> which hee would have called <hi>Religion—</hi>to have deceived weakelings therewith.—They are I ſay apparant at Sect. 71. to F: Thoſe of the Parliament at Sect. 71—from F: to 72.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> The Parliaments actions are not originally-intentionally, or volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/>, &amp;c.—but contrarily—inforcedly, for the univerſall; ſo thy particular defence, and ſo farre <hi>is juſt and approveable,</hi> and of thee to be approved of,—what's beyond I diſapprove, but its not eaſily apparent what they are:—but this remember,—that both of thy inforced ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, —ſo of thy unjuſt ſuffering by them, the <hi>Scots</hi> make the King the originall cauſe of all,—ſc—by his ſtill continued,—offenſive, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending <note place="margin">Note.</note> for the command of thy life, liberty, eſtate, and religion, &amp;c. <note place="margin">Rememher the Inſtance before in a Law ſuite, and anſwer thy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe.</note> Hee is at this inſtant, the cauſe of defence,—and ſo of thy preſſures in expences, feares—and inforcements—&amp;c. which by the <hi>Scots</hi> account—thou oughtſt put on his account, and not on the enforced defenſive State—except thou and thine wouldſt be unſtated for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> But this I dare adventure on—in behalfe of the Parliament,—that could they quit themſelves of being offended,—and aſſailed on the King ſide—that ſo all clouds were over, and the Coaſt—cleare, and the Heavens ſerene—they would make—thee, thine,—and the whole Kingdom <hi>abſolute freemen,—</hi>both in lives,—eeſtates, liberties—<note place="margin">It conduceth to their honor, end, &amp; betruſt,-ſo to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of their poſterity, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; frends, &amp;c.</note> and religion.—As for Religion, if they—allow liberty—of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which in conſcience—they ought, by <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. to allow us, <hi>let each be perſwaded in his owne conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. ſo by many other places is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable, with the cautions at Sect. 54. Thou haſt no cauſe to except at what God accepts, except thou wilt except againſt him.—Is't not faire (thou excepter) that thou ſhalt enjoy thy liberty<hi>—to Presbyter it?</hi> &amp;c. Wilt not thou retaliate,—and allow—as thou art allowed?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> From the parallell of <hi>Parliament and King</hi> aforeſaid, thou maiſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thou art as was the <hi>Iſraelites'</hi> twixt<hi>—Solomon—</hi>and <hi>Rehoboam, Solomon</hi> had uſed them hardly,—but <hi>Rehoboham</hi> projected to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate them, to bow and bend them, ſo as to make them plyant to <hi>his tyranny,—</hi>he would <hi>whip with Scorpions,—</hi>and <hi>his little finger—ſhould be more oppreſſing then his Fathers whole body.—</hi>Is it not ſo <hi>'twixt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and King? the Parliament</hi> have enforcedly oppreſt thee,—and <hi>ſo farre is juſt on their ſide,—</hi>and muſt as a fore, be charged on the K.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114919:16"/>
               <hi>not them:—</hi>but their voluntaries are like thoſe of <hi>Solomons,—</hi>the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the K. at</hi> Sect. 71. <hi>to</hi> F. Parliament <hi>Sect.</hi> 71. <hi>at</hi> F.</note> Kings <hi>are like the Intentionalls of</hi> Rehoboam.—Admit both ſides—cannot be avoided,—is it not wiſdome to leſſen our enemies,—and wiſely—take part with the leſſer,—to overthrow the greater?—which alone we cannot doe; which done, we have but—one enemie, as <hi>Solomons—hard uſages</hi> to contend with.—Conſider what I have ſaid, and be wiſe,—'twixt <hi>Solomon,—</hi>and <hi>Rehoboam</hi> you may be ruin'd,—if you ſide with both:—ſo if you ſide it ſtronglieſt with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The K. fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in Scots &amp; Forreigners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us.</note>—you fide with your ruine alſo:—but break <hi>Rehoboam</hi> to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,—and my life for thine wee ſhall all piece—together againe—in peace and plenty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This laſtly remember, the Parliament hath quit thee from all, as at 71. E. to F, &amp;c. is it nothing?—But what did the King ever doe for thee, ſhew if thou canſt?</p>
            <p>Its yet objected,—no peace or ſettlement will be till the King come <note place="margin">72. <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note>—home and be ſetled.—</p>
            <p>Its 'cauſe thy braine and witt is unſetled,—and 'cauſe knaves and <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> fooles—ſuggeſt ſeveralls to thee, out of which thy weakeneſſe cannot winde:—but of what nature ſoever thy thoughts are, or their ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions be—ſee to the contents of the particulars,—and ſo to their anſwer—and call to minde—all other particulars in this booke not referr'd to.—Help to ſettle it by ſideing with <hi>Solomon</hi> againſt <hi>Rehoboam,—</hi>as thou haſt read in the inſtances foregoing,—for thy ſelfe (if not for theirs—) ſo for the Kingdom, &amp;c. <hi>which is thy King,</hi> &amp;c. How wouldſt thou have him come home;—what like a Conquerour? If ſo, thou art a ſlave according to—Sect. 71. E. to F. See more under <hi>treaty,</hi> and take heed he conquer you not by yeelding, that may be won by ſmiles and wiles, which could not be by force and blowes.</p>
            <p>—Yet againe, thou ſaiſt, <hi>thou fighteſt for the Kingdome, thy ſelfe, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">73. <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>thine,—</hi>in fighting with,—and for the King againſt the Parliament; alſo that by Covenant, &amp;c. thou oughtſt to fight for the King, his Rights and Dues, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What thy intentions are—I know not, but thy actions in fighting <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> for the King, &amp;c. are abſolutely <hi>againſt the Kingdom, thy ſelfe, and thine,</hi> ſee 71. to F. &amp;c. See alſo the diſcrimen 'twixt Parliament and King, ſee at <hi>Sect.</hi> 71. O. to 72.</p>
            <p>For the Covenant,—thou art miſtaken,<hi>—its for the King</hi> reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively—ſee <hi>Sect.</hi> 42. to 44.—and for the Kingdome the Parliament, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Covenant the</hi> 3. <hi>it ſelfe.</hi>
               </note> ſo each particular as thy ſelfe and thine, ſo each one,<hi>—its abſolute,</hi> ſee <hi>Sect.</hi> 44.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114919:17"/>
Thou yet wilt fight againſt the Parliament as wrongers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 74.</note> the King, thy ſelfe and thine?</p>
            <p>Truly—I cannot ſee how they can wrong the King, what ever they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by the <hi>Scots</hi> ſayings he be guilty of the blood ſhed in the 3. Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, its well neare 3. or 400000. lives, are they not ſo many murthers?-for one <hi>Nabal—</hi>a <hi>Iezabel:</hi> how then?</note> doe to him,—hath he not forfeited all?-hath he not only—wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,—but ſought the ruine of all?—what ſaith <hi>lex talionis to this?—</hi>I am ſilent,—be thou judge,—can the end doe the means a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wrong,—to uſe it any way for its conducement, no juſter and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way being?—By this argument, if thou oughtſt fight againſt them as wrongers of him, which they are not,—why then not againſt the King, which is ſo in the higheſt degree, <hi>and that of his King,</hi> as at Sect. 71. to F. Why alſo not for them againſt him, by the argument at <hi>Sect.</hi> 71. O. to 72.—</p>
            <p>I have been large, cauſe I would meet with all objections,—-and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions,—and ſo ſatisfie circularly,—which I hope I have done,-and <note place="margin">75.</note> ſo I conclude with invocation and application as followeth.—</p>
            <p>I doe then implore all ſorts, even from the higheſt to the loweſt,—-as the moſt honourable Senate and City,—and the Worthies of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod:—ſo all Countries, Cities, Townes-and Villages; yea each Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall,—remember and conſider what I have ſaid, and refreſh memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by review of the Contents,—all your ſcruples—(except you will find or make knots in bul-ruſhes) are ſatisfied and cleered,—you may tuſh, piſh, ſlght,—and wrangle,—but anſwer you cannot,—ſo muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity—contend againſt <hi>the light of nature, reaſon—and juſtice,—</hi>and what are ſuch,—&amp;c?—newtralize not, as it conduceth to the univerſall,—but helpe <hi>Parliament and Army,</hi> and ſo your ſelves—againſt the King <hi>the Kingdomes Steward—&amp; ſervant,-ſo</hi> any other, &amp;c.-much more <note place="margin">Let not Judg <hi>Ienkin's</hi> book, nor any ſuch deceive you, it ſavors of much weakneſſe, or wickedneſſe, or both,—It's eaſily anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red had we leiſure.</note> take heed,-you take not up Armes againſt Parliament, or Army,-or any that is faithfull <hi>to—his, &amp; your King,</hi> the Kingdome, in behalfe of the Kingdomes Steward or any, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Land-men,—Sea-men,—ſo all ſorts of either—defame not your names, and ſo your poſterities-with the aſperſions <hi>of treacheries,-rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,-murthers,-robberies, and rapes</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">As any theſe things are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, &amp;c.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For all are guilty in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids-<hi>that-neutralize it in King</hi> Salus <hi>behalfe,</hi> much more that riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt—King <hi>Salus,</hi> &amp;c. Take heede of the depraved of the Clergie <note n="b" place="margin">Thoſe that are good of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I honour.</note>, who define the aforeſaids amiſſe <hi>in behalfe of the King?—</hi>alſo of their crying up, <hi>great is</hi> Darius <hi>and</hi> Diana,— 'cauſe they—(as the <hi>Demetrians)</hi> live by—one or both—its their own ends they aime at,-&amp; neither King
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114919:17"/>
               <hi>Darius,</hi> nor the Goddeſſe <hi>Diana—</hi>they care for, but as conducing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The ſame ends they have to deceive the devoutly religious,—but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>principled, <note place="margin">So the devout yet iggnorant noble women were ſtirred up againſt <hi>Paul</hi> under pious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note>—as <hi>Templum Domini—</hi>the Church: ſo <hi>Gods Miniſters,</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Religion,—</hi>Gods—honour,—worſhip,—ſervice, but define all theſe amiſſe,—ſo outing of all but themſelves, as Sects, Independents, &amp;c. but it may be, cannot, or will not deſcribe a right <hi>what are Sects—</hi>outable,—but for this ſee to <hi>Sect.</hi> 54. and be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Their-ſuggeſtions-are not their ends,—their ends are to end—all their oppoſers, and non-complyers under thoſe pretences-of Sects, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Seperatiſts, &amp;c. that come not under them,- 'cauſe they looſe <hi>the Soveraignty over them,—</hi>and the ſallarie of their meanes.</p>
            <p>It is ſtrongly conjectured, were it not for theſe ſufferings, by their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration,-they would ſuffer them with ſilence, &amp;c. would the State confer on them 2. or 300. l. a year certain, to officiate,-&amp;c. you ſhould finde all theſe winds &amp; ſtorms allaid, and they'd be calm'd,-when they ſee the confluence of their auditory conferred nothing,-nor the others declining them loſt them not any thing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Conſider, oh conſider then, and doe as did the Iſraelites in caſe of <note place="margin">76.</note> the Levites,-delay not, free your ſelves immediately,-and right <hi>your wronged King</hi> Salus, againſt the <hi>treacherous, perfidious,-hypocriticall, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligous-Scot</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Where are the wits of our wits, and wiſe ones, are they—ſeers—that ſee nothing? thinkes any one the wily pretending Scot—will come in for any ones end but his own? will he raiſe the King, but to be raiſed by him? will he not confluent with numbers, having two garriſon Townes for his inlets,—truly he deſignes to undermine—and bring the Engliſh to canveſſe breeches,—and wooden ſhoes—&amp;c.</note>
               <hi>:-</hi>ſo all others,-under what name and title ſoever,-ſettle the Kingdome,—ſo your ſelves, in an aſſured-ſafety,—juſtice, peace, and rights. I ſay delay not, <hi>ob State,—oh Army,-and City,—</hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <note place="margin">Diſcover the Scotch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery to all the Countries—cauſe it to be read in Churches.</note> how to raiſe all Countries (under apparent and juſt grounds)-as one man (for preſent diſpatch of theſe troubles) againſt the <hi>Scot,</hi> ſo all other enemies, and lye not lingring under languiſhing and diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting uncertainties,-be not be-fool'd, with Letters and Declarations—from any,—know you not who,-and what they are?—Know you not alſo that the Traytors, <hi>Hopton,-ſo</hi> the reſt, may thus write, and the other muſt put too his hand and ſeale,—be it one, be it all, its all to no purpoſe-with the wiſe and knowing, &amp;c. I may infinite it, but this is enough, if any thing will ſerve.</p>
            <p>Only Reader I finde it a common errour, that many Zealots eager
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114919:18"/>
of the common good,-ſpend themſelves for it,-ſo many continued uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bookes are writ,-and by the <hi>Athenian</hi> Readers eagerly read over,-that done, he hath done with the booke,-and ther's an end of all. Its alſo (cauſe little) pamphleted, &amp; under that notion, ſlighted, ſo it ſerves him not for any uſe,—no not when he hath moſt uſe of it, as being loſt,—alſo loſt to his memory: ſo that if he be tray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered or rebelled,-&amp;c. he knowe not their bounds,—ſo is bound hand and foote.—</p>
            <p>Few alſo informe their children—or friends, ſo that in a moment ignorance—betrayes all ſorts;—whereas the wiſe, that they may not be ſurprized,—would read, to remember—and diſpoſe of, ſo—as may be alwayes in a readineſſe to redreſſe the errours of ignorance, &amp;c.—Let this Memento admoniſh thee for future,—and I have my deſire, if thou haſt the benefit, which is the end of my writing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Nay Reader, over ſhooes, over bootes,—if thou wilt excuſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, <note place="margin">77.</note>—thou ſhalt have matter (which is more materiall) in its ſtead.—Wee could methodize alſo, would time allow us; but It will not, ſo we muſt as we may.—A few Miſcelanies more, and I have done,—with things that have, and if not look'd to, will undoe us.—<note place="margin">78. <hi>Pitty &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pitty &amp; compaſſion</hi> are moſt human paſſions, yet oft the <hi>moſt inhumane,</hi> cauſe not manlily managed; cannot we pitty? but we muſt precipitate <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>All for one.</hi> 'Cauſe it's call'd pitty, &amp; complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
               <hi>univerſe—for urius?—</hi>this is more cruell then cruelty it ſelfe,—but its unnaturall names and occulers, deceive our occults and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, &amp;c. The preſent obvious object is moſt poſſeſſing to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſing of all the abſents.—</p>
            <p>I have heard of one that hath beene charged with the blood-ſhed of 3. Nations,—which may amount to ſome 2. or 300000.—of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple his <hi>Creators—</hi>&amp;c.?—This Officer being alſo further engaged by oath and betruſt to protect them—yet in cold blood, projected <note place="margin">To Command all that was theirs.</note> their proſtration, that he might out them of their lives at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Yet this offending Officer—ſeeming ſorrowfull (yet not for his ſins, for he goes on,—but) at ſome reſpective ſuffering, for poſitively its none,—except great attendance and a plentifull Table be a ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp;c.—But he ſeemes moved I ſay at his ill condition,—not at his ill conditions, and its like in a cruell pitty, to procure his enlargement, and the peoples confinement.</p>
            <p>But can the engaged (by choiſe, oath, betruſt, love, and relations) to doe Juſtice, and right? do this to their loving chooſers? Doth not the Covenant alſo binde our State and the <hi>Scot,</hi> ſo all to maintaine the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114919:18"/>
Kingdomes rights? and what are they,<hi>—but juſtice,—and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> what can,—for what cannot be ſatisfied for?—Is not the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency—and honour of the Nation—a-Right? why ſhould any thing be done to its diſhonour:—ſo the States.—Will the State unſtate us of all?—is it done like a State?</p>
            <p>Did,—or could hee ſorrow and repent it were well:—but its no <note place="margin">Murthered.</note> ſatisfaction.—Conſidering the infinites, finited by him,—and his engagements as afore to the contrary,—as to protect, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If each not ſo engaged—ſhould murther one, and then ſuffer ſome <note place="margin">Thoſe were not their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers keepers as was he.</note> reſtraints, or ſuppoſe repent, muſt this procure their enlargement,—then let's all murther-one-by-one till we have gone the round.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Manaſſes</hi> repentance—if reall, is not to our point, I will not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it,—reaſon and juſtice allowes it not,—ſo then nor God.</p>
            <p>I can oppoſe with examples:—but the power is in reaſon, which examines them all, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>See at <hi>Sect.</hi> 42. 45. concerning retaliation of this kind,—&amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply—to juſtice and reaſon.</p>
            <p>Senſibleneſſe and pitty-doe well,-but to be inſenſible of the moſt pittifull object that can be objected, doth ill,—and to manage theſe <note place="margin">As ſo many murthers.</note> humane and feminine paſſions—man like, doth beſt of all.—Sure <hi>Samuel—</hi>was pittifull,—yet hee hewed <hi>Agag</hi> in pieces: and <hi>David,</hi> pittifull, yet delivered hee up 7. of <hi>Sauls</hi> innocent ſonnes to the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites for the Gibbit, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>None hath power to quit or qualifie <hi>but the wronged,—</hi>who cannot <hi>'cauſe they are not,</hi> and who are, cannot,<hi>—cauſe—they may not.—</hi>Nature, reaſon, juſtice, and the Covenant,—beſides the end of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, all I ſay, demand Juſtice, how comes it then wee are juſtled out of it? oh irreligious, atheiſticall, inhumane and bloody Nation, to drink &amp; ſwallow down at a draught ſo much blood, &amp; never reluctate.</p>
            <p>Juſtice—and retaliation—in and by juſtice, is not cruelty, <hi>its—</hi>
               <note place="margin">79. <hi>Of cruelty.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cruelty—not to be ſo cruell,</hi> it multiplies offenders, and murthers the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> nor <hi>David,</hi> as afore were not cruell, in ſatisfying Juſtice, though the act ſeeme cruell.</p>
            <p>Juſtice is the Queen of vertues, injuſtice is the Queane of vices. The firſt eſtabliſheth, the latter demoliſheth Thrones. Much may be ſaid <note place="margin">80. <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
               </note> of the aforeſaids, but we have transgreſt beyond pardon; yet if mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be pardoned, what may not?—However will not our zeal for the common good procure a pardon? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:114919:19"/>
81 We could not have conceived, had we not ſaid one word of the Kings ſubordination, as <hi>Servant, Officer,</hi> or <hi>Steward,</hi> to the <hi>State at large,</hi> that there is no underſtanding ſo ſhort, but would <hi>ſelfly</hi> (at one preſent apprehenſion) have comprehended and reacht it, but we finde it other wiſe, &amp;c.-But now that which we have ſaid, <hi>ſeconding their capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities,</hi> how can we queſtion it, but that each one is fully ſatisfied; which if yet they be not, no endevour ſhall be wanting of our ſide, &amp;c. Would God they would not in weakneſſe or wickedneſſe be wanting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and theirs, ſo to their native countrey, their true King.</p>
            <p>We ſhall then define a King,—which rightly done, will right all underſtandings but unrighteous ones.</p>
            <p>A true and righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King then, (to whom the title may be rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, is ſuch a one<hi>—who by a right ſelf-power ſelfly commands, and is ſelfly obeyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>82. A right ſelf-power—is not <hi>any</hi> ſelf-power <hi>unjuſtly inforced, gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>or uſurped.</hi> Which is thiefe-like, and Tyranny, though cal'd <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note again, <hi>A Self-power,</hi> not <hi>Deputative,—Kings it.—Selfes,</hi> are—Parents and Pay-maſters, and juſt Conquerours, &amp;c. By this no Deputy powers can be rightly cal'd Kings.</p>
            <p>All are <hi>Deputy-powers</hi> that are not <hi>Self-powers,</hi> as afore, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Who is King then? whether he that doth and ought execute the laws, <hi>The wills of</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Lawes are the wills of the State at large, or the people, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>others,</hi> and that for <hi>Them, not Himſelf:</hi> Or, thoſe that ſet thoſe Laws, <hi>alſo, enjoyns him an Oath to execute them,</hi> and none other? Alſo for <hi>Themſelves,</hi> not <hi>Himſelfe.</hi> And doe alſo allow Honours and Revennues <hi>reſpectively,</hi> as the ſaid Lawes are lookt to, not <hi>over-lookt</hi> Judge all men of what we ſay.</p>
            <p>Finde me any other uſe of a King, or any Governour, if you can,<hi>—then Juſtice, Safety, and the Welfare of the People, &amp;c.</hi> This loſt, he is <hi>uſeleſſe.</hi> For what ſaith our Saviour? <hi>Salt which hath loſt his ſavour, is uſeleſſe, and ſo good for nothing, but,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Juſt Conquerours are, <hi>Who defenſively conquer their unjuſt offending adverſaries.</hi> Theſe ſet their own Lawes, and <hi>ſo command, and are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed</hi> Selfly: and are juſtly Maſters of <hi>Liberties, Livelihoods,</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of the conquered. And this is our juſt right at this time, over thoſe Scots we have conquered in this their unjuſt <hi>Invaſion.</hi> But had they conquered us, it were <hi>Thief-like Murther and Theft,</hi> as it is nevertheleſſe in all they kill or take.</p>
            <p>83. Will you have Scripture to ſecond our Arguments in behalfe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114919:19"/>
of the <hi>Kinghood</hi> of the <hi>State at large.</hi> Whether (ſaith our Saviour, ſo St. <hi>Paul)</hi> is greater, <hi>Woman or Man?</hi> the <hi>Sabbath</hi> or <hi>Man,</hi> for whom both <hi>Woman</hi> and the <hi>Sabbath</hi> are made? Whether is greater, <hi>the God, or the Temple which ſanctifieth it?</hi> Apply, between the State and the King, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>84. Laſtly, will you have an Argument from the State or Parliament? Doe they not (King) <hi>the State at large,</hi> and Servant, and Officer the King, <hi>in their taking up Armes</hi> in loyalty to their ſaid <hi>Lord and King</hi> the Kingdome, againſt the King, <hi>ſo call'd,</hi> for his diſloyalty to the ſaid State? And doth not this taking up Armes againſt it, accuſe him of, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We from the premiſes quaere it, If Juſtice and Loyalty can allow <hi>any Self-titles of Kings, &amp;c.</hi> to any Deputy powers, to defeat the <hi>State at large</hi> of its <hi>Kinghood,—</hi>Yea, to its <hi>Serviling</hi> to its <hi>Servant?</hi> to the hazarding of <hi>Life, Liberty, and Eſtate.</hi> Conſider of it, <hi>O States,</hi> conſider of it, <hi>Steward ſends to a Lord, Vice-roy</hi> to a <hi>Roy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more I could have ſaid in poynt of Reaſon, to a full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all ſcruples and objections; but we have not time to doe it, ſo muſt contract our ſelves, <hi>though for contract underſtandings, we wiſh we could have inlarged, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>85. But we have <hi>Atheiſticall,</hi> (yet hypocriticall) adverſaries to deale withall, who will pretend Religion, &amp;c.—Theſe, however, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to conquer us by Scripture, though they cannot by Reaſon, and to ſubdue all our Reaſons, <hi>yea our Reaſon,</hi> our Senſe and our Senſes thereby, ſo they fetch out of Scripture all that ſeemingly makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, <hi>in behalfe of the King,</hi> of rather themſelves under colour of his name, and then demand of us, what we can ſay <hi>to this, to that? &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Yet the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars are anſwered, might we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit them.</note> Bidding us quit our ſelves, if we can. It were infinite to anſwer to all particulars, which cauſe we cannot, <hi>we will diſcharge our ſelves by one generall Poſition,</hi> which ſhall proſtrate all their poſitions, &amp;c. We then ſay, <hi>this of Kings and Governours,</hi> is a poynt Rationall, and of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and not of Faith: and as ſo, it <hi>falls under their Regiment for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> and not under that of Faith. So then, whatſoever is brought out of Scripture, and however rendred, muſt have a conſtruction that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with, and overthrowes not, neither <hi>Juſtice, Reaſon, nor the Senſes, &amp;c.—</hi>This is enough in it ſelfe, however, it's as much as time will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us to ſay at this preſent, &amp;c. onely we remember thee of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours and St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſayings, at Sect. 83. ſo at 42. 45. which are as ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall (though in Scripture) as are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:114919:20"/>
86. But yet againe, they have not done with us: For if neither Reaſon nor Scripture will doe the deed,<hi>—Lawleſſe Law ſhall,—</hi>So <hi>Judge Jenkins</hi> comes marching on furiouſly, <hi>Jehu-</hi>like, ſo as hee admits of no oppoſition,—and now are we (conceived) put to flight, yet are we not fled, <hi>nor will ſo much as turn our backs, &amp;c.</hi> but keep both our ſtation and poſture—and ſo make head againſt all his impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, as followeth.</p>
            <p>We have not time, I ſay, to deale with each of his particulars, <hi>which had we,</hi> we would, &amp;c.—ſo we muſt, as we may. Wee therefore in our <hi>Generall Poſition,</hi> as afore, anſwer, and ſo put to ſilence all, he or any one can ſay, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We then ſay, <hi>Law,</hi> ſo called, is <hi>the Creature of its Creator</hi> the State at large, <hi>made for its ſervice,</hi> (and not to its diſ-ſervice, much leſſe <hi>to ſervile it)</hi> by the States) <hi>the ſaid States Commiſſioners,</hi> and that is way of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Safety, ſo all other accommodations of the ſaid State, and not <hi>to the King or any other againſt it.—</hi>Now if a Law (ſo called) which ſhould be made, as afore, <hi>for the uſe of the State at large,</hi> by the ſaid States, <hi>truſted to make lawes,</hi> in behalfe of <hi>their Lord,</hi> and not in behalfe of any his ſervants <hi>againſt him,</hi> if they ſhall, I ſay, make, and ſo call that a Law, which is not ſo, <hi>as being quite contrary to their betruſt,</hi> and the end of Law, as in accommodation of ſome of their ſervants, <hi>againſt their Lord.—Quaere.</hi> If it be not abſolute treachery in them to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the liberties and rights of their Lord,</hi> to any of his Servants, &amp;c.—nay we ſay then, <hi>it's no law,</hi> though made as afore alſo, called ſo, and <hi>complemented with</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">If a known long practis'd Phyſitian pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare (as hee calls it) phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick for his patient, and ceremonies it with the complements of a viall or galli pot, and all other circumſtances, can all this make it phyſick? if apparantly deſtructive to its ends, and in ſtead of ſaving will kill, may not ſuch Phyſick be kild, &amp;c. Apply, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>ceremonials to make it paſſe ſo,—</hi>we ſay again, it's no law, ſo binds no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nor may, nor can, nor ſhall it bind <hi>the Lord,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his retainers, <hi>ſo as to be abuſed,</hi> by any his ſervants, except in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the ſaid Lord, which juſt neceſſity warranting,—is—ſufferance, no abuſe.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, we care not what <hi>Judge Jenkins,</hi> nor any, or <hi>the law it ſelfe</hi> (ſo called) ſaith or doth, or would doe, as to binde us to Kings, or any Governours (alias <hi>the kingdomes and peoples Stewards, and Servants)) if contrary or deſtructive</hi> to its ends,<hi>—the freedomes and rights of the Generall, &amp;c.</hi> whereas it ought rather to binde <hi>all Kings and Governours</hi> (who are indeed moſt bound) to accommodate the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114919:20"/>
LORD <note n="*" place="margin">The State at large.</note> GENERAL, though to their owne ſelfe-ſufferings, &amp;c. Thus much in ſhort, <hi>to Law,</hi> ſo to <hi>Judge Jenkins</hi> his large and <hi>famou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> Law-piece, moſt infamous, in that he aimes to treacherize it to his Lord and King, <hi>the State at large, &amp;c.</hi> and ſervile him to his ſervants, &amp;c. Thus our juſt, our rationall, and as ſo, our <hi>true and lawfull definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of treaſon and rebellion, &amp;c.</hi> ſtand good, againſt <hi>Judge Jenkins</hi> his unjuſt, irrationall, and deſtructive (and therefore illegall) though cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led legall-definitions, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>87. Only I will tell thee, thou h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt now no colour of ignorance left to prevaricate &amp;c. nor to beare out thy former perpetrations, <hi>Forgoe them then,</hi> and once at laſt turn wiſe and honeſt: all thy undertakings againſt, or neglect of thy <hi>Lord Salus,</hi> muſt now needs proceed from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, <hi>not impotence,—</hi>thou now knoweſt what <hi>the King,</hi> ſo called in reality, is. I hope, nor <hi>Titles,</hi> nor <hi>Names,</hi> nor <hi>rich Rayment,</hi> nor a <hi>great Train,</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> ſhall now deceive thee; <hi>Nothing</hi> can make a man <hi>more then a man,</hi> leſſe they may. <hi>A Magazine is the richeſt place indeed,—</hi>but let each fetch away his treaſure, <hi>what is it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>88. I am not factious, nor partiall, I am againſt both, <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> as they forfeit <hi>their ends and betruſts,</hi> and are againſt <hi>the kingdome.</hi> And I am for one or both as they are faithfull to their <hi>Truſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>89. More I hope I need not ſay, but yet if any ſhall in pretence of love and duty to the King (ſo call'd) alias <hi>the kingdomes Steward,</hi> be ſo treacherous to the Kingdome <hi>their true King,</hi> ſo to themſelves, their poſterities, kindred and friends, to oppoſe us, <hi>in defence of the ſaid King or Steward,</hi> againſt the kingdome, we heartily deſire them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline all baſe and treacherous ends to the aforeſaids. And if it be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their injuditious judgements (after all we have ſaid) they will recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them; and let them <hi>with ingenuity</hi> purſue <hi>the acquiring and purchaſing the truth</hi> with us, as wee will with them; and let the convinc'd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. And we further heartily intreat them, that they would, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeems the civil (if they will needs reply) perform it not perfunctorily, but with <hi>Nervous and ſtrenuous Arguments,</hi> not idle and fallacious to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the people, and loſe time, and as if they ſought rather a <hi>vainglori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conqueſt,</hi> then the true glory of truth.—Alſo that it may be without ſcurrillity or contempt, and they ſhall be anſwerably dealt with. For we hold exclamations, jeerings and contempts, to proceed of ill na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ill educations, or weakneſſe, &amp;c. like <hi>Schoole-boyes,</hi> who when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weake in diſpute, doe in wickedneſſe fall to ſcolding and fifty-cuffs, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Dixi.</hi> Onely, <hi>If nothing will do, we are undone, and ſo are moſt of our undoers.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114919:21"/>
         </div>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:114919:21"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>AN APOLOGIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S we have Cautioned in caſe any write againſt us, &amp;c. So we hold it neceſſary alſo, to ſay ſomething; leſt any one <hi>in a pretence of love and loyalty</hi> to the King or Kingdomes <hi>Steward,</hi> although it may be <hi>Demetrian ſelfe-love,</hi> and not to <hi>Diana,-alſo, hate to</hi> Paul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be the true ground, <hi>and not love to the King:—</hi>but admit, love, &amp;c. to him—its not right nor juſt <hi>in oppoſition to</hi> his King, <hi>the Kingdome.—</hi>However, leaſt they ſhould in a <hi>purpoſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> upon us, under the pretences aforeſaid, ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This man writes againſt the King;</hi> alſo diſhonours him, &amp;c. by <hi>meane</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Objection.</note> 
               <hi>expreſſions and rendrings;</hi> alſo <hi>intimates</hi> this or that of him, &amp;c. Alſo the title is tart and offenſive.</p>
            <p>To the aforeſaids I anſwer as followeth. To the laſt, firſt. If the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> ſhould offend thee; <hi>yet be not offended,—</hi>For thou either haſt, or wilt finde, that thoſe who conſpire againſt <hi>the Welfare, Crowne, Peace, and Dignity</hi> of our Soveraigne Lord <hi>King Salus,</hi> are farre worſe <hi>then Knaves,</hi> for they are Traytors; why then ſhould we fear <hi>to offend them?</hi> And thoſe who are enſnared or deluded by them; may they not, <hi>right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> (at the leaſt) be cal'd Fooles.</p>
            <p>And to the former objection, I anſwer, I doe not <hi>intentionally</hi> to wrong, diſhonour, or abate any thing of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewards <hi>juſt Dues and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The neglect of others ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesſitates us.</note> 
               <hi>Rights,—</hi>but what I muſt doe of neceſſity <hi>in defence and vindication of King Salus.</hi> And if ſo he ſuffer, it's ſufferable;—what alſo, if it be <hi>his inſufferables,</hi> are the cauſe of <hi>his ſufferings?</hi> But ther's not any thing his due, <hi>in oppoſition to</hi> the Kingdomes ſufferance, <hi>in ſafety, juſtice, and Rights,—</hi>for if more be given him, then his due, <hi>to the wronging of the univerſall,—</hi>ſo particulars,—in their <hi>Rights</hi> of Juſtice and ſafety, &amp;c. <hi>Reaſon, Juſtice, &amp; neceſſity</hi> require, a reducing all <hi>to rights, that</hi> ſo hee may have his owne due, and not beyond; eſpecially <hi>to the encroachment upon</hi> what's his Lords, <hi>the Kingdomes.</hi> However, if he ſhould loſe any of <hi>his juſt Rights</hi> for <hi>Salus</hi> ſake, <hi>its juſt and right.—</hi>But if it be <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and juſtice</hi> in any thus to plead for his Rights; <hi>How is't,</hi> they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114919:22"/>
plead not for the Rights of <note n="*" place="margin">Here's <hi>adoo</hi> about <hi>the King the King,</hi> with pretences of love &amp; loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to him, &amp;c.—Well,—now <hi>we have</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you <hi>the true &amp; right King,—</hi>make good <hi>your precences,—</hi>elſe you are only <hi>a Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the true King indeed?</hi> to whom they are <hi>firſt and principally bound</hi> in nature and reaſon,—ſo by Covenant the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> &amp;c.<hi>—So it appears to be craft,</hi> not conſcience.</p>
            <p>Nor doe we intimate any thing <hi>injuriouſly</hi> againſt him, for <hi>Deſerts are no injuries;—</hi>only we inferre, from the Scots ſayings, <hi>and their taking up Arms againſt him,—</hi>ſo from <hi>our States</hi> taking up Armes alſo, <hi>and traytering thoſe that ſide with him</hi> againſt the <hi>States:</hi> and thus <hi>both States Actions</hi> are directions <hi>and Warrants</hi> for us, what we may ſay &amp; doe; For, if we are enjoyned <hi>to fight againſt him,—</hi>ſure its as he is, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.—Sure alſo, we are <hi>enjoyned,</hi> and ſo may <hi>ſpeake and write</hi> as well as <hi>fight,—</hi>the laſt being <hi>the leſſer</hi> of the two, and contained in, the <hi>Greater—</hi>fighting, &amp;c.—being alſo never forbid,—and were wee forbid, we conceive <hi>forbiddings cannot juſtly diſcharge us</hi> of our juſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>to our Lord and King the State.—</hi>Again, to forbid us, were to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid <hi>the Covenant,</hi> which alſo enjoynes us, <hi>as doth reaſon and juſtice alſo,</hi> to ſupport the Kingdomes rights <hi>firſt and abſolutely.</hi> The Stewards <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily,</hi> reſpectively and conducingly:<hi>—but what rights are due, to</hi> univerſall wrong-doers?</p>
            <p>Now the kingdoms Rights are <hi>ſafety, peace, and juſtice,—</hi>ſo to have its honour maintained, and its innocency <hi>cleared,—</hi>though the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard <hi>ſhould ſuffer in his honour</hi> or any way, for the accommodation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,—how then if the ſufferance be juſt?—For <hi>the means</hi> muſt ſuffer for <hi>the End,</hi> and any way is juſt, that neceſſarily conduceth to it. And how can we <hi>be able</hi> to make good the Covenant, except the means that conduceth thereto <hi>be allowed?</hi> that is, <hi>to ſpeake, write, and act</hi> any right things <hi>in behalfe thereof,</hi> and to oppoſe any its oppoſers whoſoever.—Alſo to render <hi>the Steward</hi> in ſuch expreſſions, <hi>as that</hi> his condition &amp; place may be plainly diſtinguiſht <hi>from that</hi> of his <hi>Lords,—</hi>who muſt be allowed <hi>rendrings thereafter,</hi> that his dues may be rendred him.</p>
            <p>Again, we are <hi>neceſſitated</hi> to what we have done, and its <hi>our offenſive Adverſaries</hi> that write all this, <hi>not we,</hi> by enforcing us to write it;—<note place="margin">Shall any one or any thing bind us <hi>from defending our King,</hi> being clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that it's our duty and high time to ſpeak? <hi>God forbid.</hi>
               </note> for if <hi>treacherous bookes</hi> be writ, and opinions held <hi>ſo generally</hi> to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of King <hi>Salus,</hi> is't not treachery in all, not to beſtir themſelves (in their power and place) <hi>in his behalfe?</hi> And ſhall <hi>ſuch wicked treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ones</hi> goe unpuniſhed? and ſhall <hi>the loyall Defenders</hi> (forced by ſuch diſloyall offenders) <hi>ſuffer, &amp;c.—</hi>truly, better is expected, &amp;c. though we will not <hi>preſume</hi> to ſay what.</p>
            <p>So now we have done, and appeale <hi>to juſtice and ingenuity,</hi> hoping <hi>our love, duty and zeale</hi> to our Lord, King <hi>Salus</hi> (which in the preſence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114919:22"/>
of God, is our only aime) will ſave us from any rigid cenſures, of any our <hi>triviall ſlips and failings</hi> in his behalfe, &amp;c. In which we being Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,—muſt needs humanize it.—If now <hi>wee ſuffer</hi> by injurious Cenſures, &amp;c. its as Martyrs, &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="cautions">
               <head>Two Cautions for thy better underſtanding this Booke, which ſhould have beene placed at the beginning.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p n="1">1. WHerever thou readeſt or heareſt the expreſſions, <hi>Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, People, State at large,</hi> or Salus Populi, &amp;c. thou wouldſt in thy mind, put in their places <hi>Kings, Prince, Soveraign,</hi> yea Emperour, or <hi>Gods Anointed,</hi> &amp;c. or any rendrings <hi>as high as thou canſt;</hi> for there is none higher, <hi>but God Himſelfe;</hi> not Religion, <hi>his honour, worſhip, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, &amp;c.—</hi>as ſee in <hi>Quaere,</hi> before 66. alſo at 83. So, <hi>Salus</hi> is Head, Chiefe, &amp;c. And ſo do thou apply in thy thoughts,—ſo in thy actions, &amp;c. This we ſay is <hi>the right King,</hi> to whom <hi>the Name</hi> is due,—and to whom <hi>thou oweſt more</hi> then thou canſt pay, and for whom <hi>thou maiſt pay any one,</hi> be it whom it will, if juſtly occaſioned in his behalfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Again, whereever thou heareſt or readeſt the Titles, <hi>King, Prince, Gods Anointed,</hi> Sac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jeſtie, <hi>or Soveraign,</hi> &amp;c. in their ſtead, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in thy mind, <hi>Stew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd, Servant,</hi> or <hi>Officer</hi> to the aforeſaid <hi>Lord and King,</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> right, by all the preceding arguments. The Contents will ſend thee whereto make good both the aforeſaids. <hi>Val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:114919:23"/>
            <head>A further Addition or continuation of the Contents of the Booke for better direction, and ſatisfaction, which through haſt were left out at the firſt.</head>
            <p>17. THe Scots chiefe arguments for their Invaſion, anſwered at <hi>Sect.</hi> 37. to 45.</p>
            <p>18. The Scots <hi>charge the King</hi> with the blood-ſhed of 3. Nations,—ſo doe they charge—him alſo in their taking up Armes againſt him, &amp;c. by both which they accuſe him, ſo and ſo, &amp;c.—From whence may much be inferd,—and this amongſt the reſt, <hi>that the wel-fare, juſtice, peace, &amp; ſafety of the State,</hi> is—King, Chiefe, &amp;c. <hi>and the King</hi> a ſervant thereta,<hi>—Sect.</hi> 55.</p>
            <p>19. Some cauſes of the Peoples riſing, &amp;c. explained at Sect. 58. to 59.</p>
            <p>20. Of oaths, &amp;c. made to the King, when binding, when not, at Sect. 66.</p>
            <p>21. An anſwer in behalfe of the State, to a Catalogue of Exorbitances charged upon them,<hi>—Sect.</hi> 71. at <hi>M,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>22. The State and King <hi>diſcrimen'd,</hi> ſhewing what the King hath done,—and intended to doe againſt the kingdom, but not any thing <hi>freely,</hi> for its good. Alſo, what the State hath done for us—and what accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt us. examined at <hi>Sect.</hi> 71. all, eſpecially at <hi>O. &amp; S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>23. Pitty and Compaſſion at <hi>Sect.</hi> 78. Cruelty,—at <hi>Sect.</hi> 79. Juſtice,—at <hi>Sect.</hi> 80. rightly defined.</p>
            <p>24. A true King, <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uly defined.—</hi>Sect. 81. to 83.</p>
            <p>25. The State at large proved <hi>King, chiefe, head,</hi> &amp;c. by Scripture,—which is reaſon alſo,—and the King—(ſo called) <hi>is the ſaid Kings</hi> Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard—and Servant, &amp;c. 83.<hi>—the end</hi> there, <hi>being King and Chiefe, &amp;c.—</hi>the Meanes,<hi>—Meaner,—</hi>as—ſervant, to the Lord, <hi>its end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>26. All that may be collected out of Scripture, <hi>in behalfe of the King,—</hi>anſwered in a poſition, at Sect. 85.—</p>
            <p>17. Judge Jenkins, <hi>all of him in the Kings behalfe,—</hi>anſwered by a Poſition, Sect. 86.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
